<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A replication to a late book written by Mr. Benjamin Keach against infants-baptism intituled A counter-antidote, &amp;c. By Gyles Shute of Lime-house.</title>
            <author>Shute, Giles, b. 1650 or 51.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 131 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 42 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60172</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3712</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R221469</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99832771</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99832771</idno>
            <idno type="VID">37245</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60172)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 37245)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2060:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A replication to a late book written by Mr. Benjamin Keach against infants-baptism intituled A counter-antidote, &amp;c. By Gyles Shute of Lime-house.</title>
                  <author>Shute, Giles, b. 1650 or 51.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>72 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for the author: published and sold by Randal Taylor near Stationers-Hall, and Nath. Hiller in Leaden-hall-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Below imprint: Price three pence.</note>
                  <note>A reply to: Keach, Benjamin.  A counter-antidote to purge out the malignant effects of a late counterfeit.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Keach, Benjamin, 1640-1704. --  Counter-antidote to purge out the malignant effects of a late counterfeit --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Anabaptists --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:37245:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:37245:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A REPLICATION TO A Late BOOK Written By Mr. <hi>Benjamin Keach</hi> AGAINST Infants-Baptiſm, INTITULED <hi>A Counter-Antidote,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Gyles Shute</hi> of <hi>Lime-houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the Author: Publiſhed and Sold by <hi>Randal Taylor</hi> near <hi>Stationers-Hall,</hi> and <hi>Nath. Hiller</hi> in <hi>Leaden-hall-ſtreet,</hi> 1694. Price Three Pence.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:37245:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:37245:2"/>
            <head>A REPLICATION TO A Late BOOK Written By Mr. <hi>Benjamin Keach</hi> AGAINST Infants-Baptiſm.</head>
            <p>SIR, I have carefully peruſed your Book, and I find that you have dealt very diſinge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuouſly by me, and have made ſeveral un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind Steps upon my Credit and Reputation, which is not at all becoming a Chriſtian, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially one of your Figure.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Your whole Book is reducible to five General Heads. The <hi>Firſt</hi> is againſt our Mode of Baptiſm, <hi>viz.</hi> ſprinkling or pouring water in Baptiſm, and to prove that Dipping or Immerſion is the only Mode in Baptiſm. <hi>Secondly,</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:37245:3"/>To invalid the Notion of Habitual Faith in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect dying Infants, and to prove they are ſaved without it. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> To prove the Diſſolution of the Everlaſting Covenant God made with <hi>Abraham</hi> and all his Seed, calling it a Covenant of Circumciſion only. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> To prove that none but Adult Believers are the Subjects of Baptiſm. <hi>Fifthly</hi> and Laſtly, To prove that the Church-State, before the coming in of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, was only a carnal Legal Church-State, and therefore deſtroyed and diſſolved by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>Now upon theſe Five Pillars your Opinion is built, and from theſe five Topicks are all your Arguments raiſed and deduced againſt us Paedo-baptiſts; wherefore to confute theſe five Heads is to Anſwer all your Book.</p>
            <p>But before I enter upon the controverſie I muſt acquaint the Reader with ſome of Mr. <hi>Keach</hi>'s unkind Steps he hath made upon my Credit and Reputation, which I conceive was to render me as black and odious in the Eye of the World as poſſibly he could: So that what I have written in Vindication of Infant-baptiſm, and the Everlaſting Covenant God made with <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> might meet with the leſs eſteem among People of all Perſwaſions. But however Truth will be Truth ſtill, notwithſtanding all the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition that is made againſt it by Men of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Principles.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Saith Mr. <hi>B. K. This Man hath come too near to the Expreſſions and bitter Reflections</hi> John Child <hi>uttered againſt us, falſely called</hi> Anabaptiſts, <hi>who ſoon after fell under fearful horrour of Conſcience and Deſperation,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And pray obſerve how his Reverend Brother <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. (as he calls him) and he are agreed; for,</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:37245:3"/>
            <p>In <hi>pag.</hi> 11. of his late Book he ſaith, <hi>Is not this the Man</hi> David <hi>ſpake of, that travelled with Iniquity, conceived Miſchief, and brought forth Falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood? Remember, remember</hi> John Child, <hi>whoſe chief cauſe of deſperation</hi> was <hi>his ſpeaking and wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting againſt thoſe</hi> very <hi>People of God you now do.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here you ſee theſe two Reverend Brethren are both agreed in their Verdict againſt me, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in Anſwer unto it, I will lay down ſome of the chief things which were the cauſe of his Deſperation, and it may be we may find one Mr. <hi>H. C.</hi> among the Witneſſes unto it in Print, and then I will leave it to all thoſe who have read my Book, to judge whether I am not moſt hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribly abuſed by theſe two Gentlemen: And for the full clearing up of this Matter, I have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured their own <hi>Parties</hi> Teſtimony to witneſs againſt them, in that Book which was written and atteſted by Mr. <hi>Thomas Plant</hi> and Mr. <hi>Benj. Dennis,</hi> concerning the cauſe of Mr. <hi>John Child</hi>'s Deſperation.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Mr. <hi>Dennis</hi> in <hi>pag.</hi> 10. ſaith, <hi>He freely diſcourſed the Grief of his Mind, expreſſing and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting forth his Condition to be moſt deplorable, as having no hope of Salvation. I laid before him, with the greateſt tenderneſs, the Freeneſs and Riches of Gods Grace, chuſing to argue from his own former declared Opinion againſt Limiting of it, but could faſten no word of conſolation or hope upon him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Here is the Teſtimony of Mr. <hi>H. C.</hi> himſelf, in <hi>pag.</hi> 18. <hi>Mr.</hi> Child, <hi>I am informed your Trouble ariſes from the Publiſhing a Book, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled,</hi> The Second Argument, <hi>&amp;c. What part of that Book troubles you moſt? Mr.</hi> Child <hi>taking up the Book, began to read, where he ſaith,</hi> The great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt number of Diſſenters do hold Principles dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerouſly Heretical, and moſt abominably abuſing
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:37245:4"/>the moſt Holy and Bleſſed God, <hi>&amp;c. But before he could end that Paragraph, being under extream agony of mind, and weeping bitterly, put the Book from him, and ſpake to this effect,</hi> viz. I have repreſented thoſe of <hi>Calvin</hi>'s Principles beyond what ever they conceived, ſtrained their Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions beyond their Intentions, and drawn ſuch Conſequences as never were in their Mind; <hi>and ſtriking his Breaſt with much anguiſh, ſaid,</hi> Theſe words lie cloſe; I ſhall never get over this I writ in prejudice againſt them, calling them a <hi>Villainous Body of People,</hi> which was unjuſt.</p>
            <p>Thirdly and Laſtly, to name no more, in <hi>pag.</hi> 26. ſaid one of the Company that was with him, <hi>It may be your Endeavours heretofore, too much to advance Free-will and the Power of the Creature, may be one reaſon why the Lord hath permitted you thus to fall.</hi> Mr. <hi>Child</hi> replied, <hi>You have hit it, Sir: I once thought there was a power in Man, but now I find it otherwiſe; for I cannot pray; the Lord hath taken away the Gift of Prayer from me; I have no deſire after any thing that is good; I cannot repent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Child</hi> did not write againſt the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> as ſuch; but he writ againſt the <hi>Calviniſts,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all perſwaſions, that hold Election and Predeſtination; therefore how could theſe Men declare to the World in Print, contrary to their own Teſtimony, that Mr. <hi>Child</hi>'s chiefeſt cauſe of Deſperation was his ſpeaking and writing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe <hi>very</hi> People of God I now do? Pray who is the Man <hi>David</hi> ſpake of, they or I? Did I ever write againſt the Free Grace of God? Pray do me the Juſtice as to read the <hi>Vindication of the Antidote, pag.</hi> 167 to 173. and ſee whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I am an <hi>Arminian,</hi> or not, as both theſe
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:37245:4"/>Gentlemen ſlily inſinuate; for Mr. <hi>Child</hi> was ſo, to whom they have compared me.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In <hi>pag.</hi> 2. ſaith Mr. <hi>K. I think few men who have had to do with us in this Controverſie ſhewed a more ſour Spirit than Mr.</hi> Baxter: <hi>And yet, did he ever deny us to be True Churches, or call our Baptiſm counterfeit?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I Anſwer, He hath called it worſe. Let any Man read Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Book of <hi>Plain Scripture-proof of Infants Church-memberſhip and Baptiſm,</hi> in <hi>chap.</hi> 13. <hi>pag.</hi> 136 and 137. there Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> hath charged the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> with being guilty of breaking the <hi>Seventh Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> in their Dipping Women and Maids (as he Phraſes it) either naked, or, as the Modeſteſt of them do, next to naked; and he calls their Baptiſm it ſelf Intolerable Wickedneſs, and not Gods Ordinance; and if your Baptiſm be In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable Wickedneſs, then your Congregations cannot be True Churches: So that in this Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> denies your Churches to be True Churches, and affirms your Baptiſm to be worſe than coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In <hi>pag.</hi> 23. ſaith Mr. <hi>K. One that read Mr.</hi> Shute<hi>'s Book obſerved, and told me, he hath writ near</hi> 20 <hi>Leaves, to no purpoſe, to prove that which No body denies,</hi> viz. <hi>That the Covenant of Grace God promiſed to</hi> Abraham <hi>is not Diſſolved,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>This looks as if Mr. <hi>K.</hi> had not read my Book himſelf, but did anſwer it by hear-ſay, becauſe he ſaith, that one told him ſo. Indeed Mr. <hi>H. C.</hi> did ſay ſo in his half-ſheet he printed againſt me, and my Anſwer to him ſhall ſerve for an Anſwer to you, which was as followeth,</p>
            <p>Mr. C. <hi>ſaith, That I ſpent</hi> 20 <hi>Leaves in proving that which No body denies,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:37245:5"/>
            <p>Theſe 20 Leaves they ſpeak of, begin at <hi>pag.</hi> 74. which I ſpent in proving that all the Infant-Seed of Believers, now under the Goſpel, are all in the ſame Covenant, with their Parents, which God made with <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed, both ſpiritual and carnal, in <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they have a Right to the Ordinance of Baptiſm. Now if No body denies this, How comes it to paſs that there is any ſuch thing as an <hi>Anabaptiſt</hi> in <hi>England?</hi> So that <hi>Anabaptiſm</hi> it ſelf hath reſigned up the ghoſt, and this may ſerve for its <hi>Funeral Sermon.</hi> As in <hi>pag.</hi> 20. of my <hi>Replication</hi> to Mr. <hi>H. C</hi>'s half ſheet.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Saith Mr. <hi>K. Mr.</hi> Shute <hi>hath leſt part of the Words in ſome Texts, and added words in other he hath quoted. See</hi> pag. 120. <hi>where he mentions the words of that Text,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.22. For as in Adam all die, ſo in Chriſt ſhall all be made alive; <hi>he has wrote thus,</hi> For as in Adam all the Elect die, ſo in Chriſt they ſhall all be made alive.</p>
            <p>I have not mentioned the Text at all in that place, but I ſaid by way of deduction thus, For as in <hi>Adam</hi> all the Elect died, and not <hi>die,</hi> (as he ſaith) ſo in Chriſt they ſhall all be made alive. Theſe were my words exactly, no more nor no leſs. Now let any Man of Sence judge whether this be any addition to, or detraction from the Text, when I did not ſo much as name it, nor intend any perverſion of the Sence of it; for will any Man ſay, that all the Elect did not die in the firſt <hi>Adam?</hi> And will any one deny that they ſhall not all be made alive in Chriſt Jeſus, the ſecond <hi>Adam?</hi> Did I ſay that none but the Elect died in <hi>Adam,</hi> and that none but ſuch ſhall be raiſed up at the Day of Judgment? This is a moſt unworthy Prevarication.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:37245:5"/>
            <p n="5">5. Saith Mr. <hi>K.</hi> in <hi>pag.</hi> 37, <hi>So in pag.</hi> 133. <hi>mentioning</hi> Mark 16.16. <hi>viz.</hi> He that believeth, and is baptized, ſhall be ſaved; but he that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth not ſhall be damned: <hi>He hath wrote it thus, viz.</hi> He that believeth ſhall be ſaved; but he that believeth not ſhall be damned.</p>
            <p>Pray Reader mark, He ſaid I mentioned <hi>Mark</hi> 16.16. which is abominable falſe alſo: I refer you to my Book, and <hi>pag.</hi> 133. aforeſaid, where you will find it thus written, <hi>viz. 15th.</hi> That there were two Covenants from <hi>Adam</hi> to the coming of Chriſt, and from thence to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of the <hi>Jews</hi> at Chriſts Second Coming, and to the End of the World, I do own; and they are the ſame from the making of them as with <hi>Adam,</hi> only that of Works was then bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, though they have paſſed through various Diſpenſations and Declarations; but the State of both is the ſame: <hi>He that believeth ſhall be ſaved; but he that believeth not ſhall be damned.</hi> So it was from <hi>Adam</hi> to this Day, and ever will be to the End of the World. Theſe were my very words, without mentioning any Text at all; for it had been Non-ſence for me to mention Baptiſm in the firſt Declaration of the Covenant with <hi>Adam,</hi> 4000 Years before that Ordinance was Inſtituted.</p>
            <p n="6">6. In <hi>pag.</hi> 30. ſaith Mr. <hi>K. I promiſed to forbear hard words, but a man that argueth thus ſhould be ſeverely dealt with, one way or another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is well for me that this Man hath not an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition at his beck and command, for if he had I could promiſe my ſelf but little favour at his hands. Pray, Sir, give me leave to tell you, you have broken your promiſe over and over many times already in theſe few things, inſtead of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, that I have here cited; for if Calumnies are
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:37245:6"/>not hard words, I do not know what are.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Saith Mr. <hi>K.</hi> quoting part of my words in <hi>pag.</hi> 4. viz. <hi>I will not render Railing for Railing,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>I ſhall labour to declare in the Spirit of meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Hath he been as good as his word?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>I have been as good as my word; but it is a very great fault in you that you quote Authors ſo as to pervert the ſenſe of their Words: And therefore I will lay down the words fairly, as they lie in my Book, in their full Latitude and Extent, which had a Reference to Mr. <hi>H. C</hi>'s. abuſive opprobrious Language, which is in his Book againſt me:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 4, 5. But I bleſs God, I can bear all your Reproaches and Calumnies chearfully, and it ſhall no ways diſcourage me, nor hinder me from vindicating the Truth, and contending earneſtly for the Faith once delivered to the Saints; and I will not render Railing for Rail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but what I have to offer in Vindication of Infants Baptiſm, and the Everlaſting Covenant God declared and made with <hi>Abraham,</hi> I ſhall labour to declare in the Spirit of Meekneſs, only ſometimes you muſt expect a gentle Touch, to put you in mind how groſly you have abuſed me, and in ſome things, where it cannot be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voided but I muſt grate a little ſmartly upon you, there you muſt bear with me, although I ſhould accoſt you in the moſt ſenſible parts, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe otherwiſe I cannot Vindicate the Honour and Glory of the Grace of God, nor my own Credit and Reputation. Now let any Man read Mr. <hi>Collins</hi>'s Book, and mine alſo, and ſee if I have not been as good as my word.</p>
            <p n="8">8. And <hi>Laſtly,</hi> Whereas it is ſaid in the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face of Mr. <hi>H. C</hi>'s. Book, <hi>viz. Here thou haſt the Cavils and Objections of the Adverſary anſwered.</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:37245:6"/>2. <hi>Infants, or little children, proved to have no Habitual Faith.</hi> 3. <hi>The Diſſolution of the Old Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant-State demonſtrated.</hi> 4. <hi>And the Infants of Believers to have no right, as the Seed of ſuch, to holy Baptiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Cavils and Objections of the Adverſary are placed to my Account by Mr. <hi>K.</hi> which is very unfair. Thus you ſee by theſe Eight un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind Steps, what kind of Spirit this man is of; and you may meaſure, not only <hi>Hercules,</hi> but alſo <hi>Benjamin</hi> by his Foot. Thus having premi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and taken a view of theſe things, I now proceed to the matter in hand.</p>
            <p>And in the firſt place I ſhall begin with the Mode of Baptiſm, Mr. <hi>B. K.</hi> hath ſpent his firſt Chapter wholly in labouring to prove, That Baptiſm is onely by Dipping or Immerſion of the Subject all under Water, and that any other Mode is no Baptiſm; and to prove it to be ſo, he hath quoted ſeveral Eminent Paedobaptiſts, ſome of which are dead, and ſome living: But I find he is ſo ſubject to miſtake, both in quoting Authors and Scriptures, that I dare not lay any weight upon what he ſays of them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In <hi>pag.</hi> 4. ſaith Mr. <hi>K. I ſhall begin with Mr.</hi> S. <hi>pag.</hi> 5. <hi>viz.</hi> I think there is more to be ſaid for ſprinkling or pouring water on the Face in Baptiſm, then there is for dipping or ducking over head and ears in a River or Pond; for the latter is more like a puniſhment of Criminals than the ſolemnizing of an Ordinance of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I Anſwer, I am of the ſame mind ſtill, and can ſee no reaſon at all to alter it; for you cannot produce any poſitive Command for it, nor clear Example of it, in all the Book of God; but the Learned will tell you, that the word <hi>Baptize,</hi> is frequently uſed for pouring and waſhing with water.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:37245:7"/>
            <p n="2">2. What was the ſignification of all thoſe Sprinklings, and Pourings, and Waſhings, with Blood, and alſo with Water, but to ſet forth and Typifie the cleanſing Vertue of the Holy Ghoſt, and the abſolute neceſſity of Regeneration and Sanctification? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 52.15. <hi>So ſhall he ſprinkle many nations,</hi> &amp;c. that is, God will ſanctifie many Nations, or ſome of many Nations; and what is Baptiſm but a Sign or Token of Sanctification and Regeneration, <hi>Exod.</hi> 24.8. <hi>And Moſes took the blood and ſprinkled it on the people, and ſaid, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the blood of the covenant, which the Lord hath made with you.</hi> And yet that was but the Sign of the Blood of the Covenant; for the real Blood of the Covenant was the Blood of Chriſt, who was given for a Covenant of the People, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.6, 8. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.13. <hi>For if the blood of bulls, and of goats, and the aſhes of an heifer ſprinkling the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean, ſanctifieth to the purifying of the fleſh.</hi> Mind, it was but the purifying of the Fleſh, not the Spirit; it was but an External Sanctification, or a Sign thereof; and is Water-baptiſm any more? But mind the <hi>14th. verſe, How much more ſhall the blood of Chriſt, who through the eternal Spirit, offered himſelf without ſpot to God, purge your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences from dead works to ſerve the living God?</hi> Ezek. 36.25, 26. <hi>Then will I ſprinkle clean water upon you, and ye ſhall be clean: from all your filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and from all your idols will I cleanſe you. A new heart alſo will I give you, and a new ſpirit will I put within you, and I will take away the stony heart out of your fleſh, and I will give you an heart of fleſh.</hi> And I pray mind all theſe following Scriptures of Sprinkling and Pourings, <hi>&amp;c. Heb.</hi> 12.24. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.2. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 44.3. <hi>Exod.</hi> 29.16, 20, 21. <hi>Levit.</hi> 1.5, 11. <hi>chap.</hi> 9.18. <hi>chap.</hi> 32.8, 13. <hi>ch.</hi> 4.6, 17. <hi>ch.</hi> 5.9. <hi>ch.</hi> 8.11, 24. <hi>chap.</hi> 14.7, 8, 9,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:37245:7"/>16, 51. <hi>Numb.</hi> 19.18, 19, 20, 21. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.22. <hi>chap.</hi> 30. 16. Here you ſee are ſprinklings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> both of blood and water, under the Old Teſtament, and alſo the New, which Types out Regeneration, <hi>viz.</hi> blood for Juſtification, and water for Sanctification, which is very compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible to the ſignification of Baptiſm. Now pray find us out ſo many Scriptures, if you can, wherein Dipping, or Immerſion in blood and water, do ſo nearly repreſent and parallel the Ordinance of Water-baptiſm, and alſo that have the Covenant for their Center, as all theſe I quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted have, both in the Old and New Teſtament.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is a practice among the <hi>Heathens</hi> (as I have been informed) when they Dedicate any thing to their <hi>Idol-Gods,</hi> to take it and dip or plunge it all under water; and if ſo, then it is plainly forbidden in <hi>Levit.</hi> 20.23. <hi>And ye ſhall not walk in the manners of the nations, which I cast out before you:</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Suppoſe, for Arguments ſake, that it ſhould be granted, That dipping in Baptiſm was the Mode in thoſe Hot Countries, where it could not be ſo prejudicial to their Health, yet it doth not therefore follow, that Perſons ſhould be dipped all under water in theſe Northern Countries, where it is ſo extream cold, eſpecially in the Winter, unleſs there had been a poſitive Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand given for ſo doing; for Baptiſm is a Duty at all times of the Year; for God never Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed any Ordinance that would put his People in Jeopardy of their Lives.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> will have Dipping to be the only Mode of Baptiſm: For, ſay they, <hi>John baptized in Enon near Salim, becauſe there was much water there:</hi> But the Learned do tell us, that it ſhould be read thus, <hi>viz.</hi> Becauſe there
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:37245:8"/>were many waters there; And ſo I have it alſo in a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Teſtament, which I may as well make uſe of as Mr. <hi>B. K.</hi> hath of the <hi>Dutch</hi> Tongue, <hi>Viz.</hi> John 3.23. <hi>Y Baptizava Tambien Juan en Enon junto a Salim, porque Avia muchas Aguas: y venian y eran Baptizados.</hi> If it had been <hi>much water</hi> then it muſt have been <hi>mucho agua,</hi> in the ſingular, and not <hi>muchas aguas,</hi> which is <hi>many waters,</hi> in the plural: And Travellers that have been in thoſe Countries do ſay, that there is ſcarcely water enough to cover a Mans Ancles, much leſs to bury their Bodies.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Another Scripture they lay great ſtreſs upon for Dipping is, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.4. <hi>Therefore we are buried with him by baptiſm,</hi> &amp;c. In which Text is Typed out unto us the new Birth, which conſiſts of two parts, namely, the death of Sin, and the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of Spiritual Life, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And both theſe are pointed at in Baptiſm, as a Sign thereof; and ſo it was in Circumciſion; both which you have repreſented together, to the ſame purpoſe, in <hi>Col.</hi> 2.10, 11, 12. which ſeems alſo to refer to, or point out unto us the change of the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance from Circumciſion to Baptiſm, <hi>viz. And ye are complete in him, which is the head of all principality and power. In whom alſo ye are circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed with the circumciſion made without hands, in putting off the body of the ſins of the fleſh, by the circumciſion of Chriſt: Buried with him in baptiſm, wherein alſo you are riſen with him through the faith of the operation of God, who hath raiſed him from the dead.</hi> Ver. 13, 14. <hi>And you being dead in your ſins, and the uncircumciſion of your fleſh, hath he quickened together with him, having forgiven you all treſpaſſes, Blotting out the hand-writing of ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, that was againſt us, which was contrary to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:37245:8"/>us, and took it out of the way, nailing it to his croſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here are ſeveral things to be obſerved from theſe Scriptures: </p>
            <p>1. Here is Circumciſion and Baptiſm, both pointing at one and the ſame thing, <hi>viz.</hi> The death of the body of Sin for all the Elect of God, vertually in the death of Chriſt, and the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of their Spiritual Life when Chriſt aroſe from the dead, which is the Firſt Reſurrection, on whom the Second Death ſhall have no power; for under the Figure of Circumciſion it is ſaid, — <hi>putting off the body of the ſins of the fleſh.</hi> Secondly, Under the Figure of Baptiſm it is <hi>[buried with him in baptiſm,]</hi> which is the death and burial of Sin.</p>
            <p>2. Here was the total Abolition of the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial Law, but not of the Moral Law; for the ſubſtantial part of the <hi>Ten Commandments</hi> are as much in force, and as binding now, as ever; and likwiſe of Circumciſion, the Token of the Everlaſting Covenant which is centered in the Ordinance of Baptiſm.</p>
            <p>3. This deſtroys their Argument, <hi>viz. That Perſons do act Grace in their own Baptiſm:</hi> For what Analogy can there be in Burial, which they make the Pattern for their Mode of Baptiſm, wherein the Subject is wholly paſſive, ſo as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be more; and being active in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, here the former part of their Argument contradicts and deſtroys the latter part thereof.</p>
            <p>4. The ſubſtance of theſe Scriptures do not only make more for us, who do affirm That all the Subjects of Baptiſm are wholly paſſive in the Adminiſtration thereof, but alſo it points out unto us the very ſubjects themſelves, namely, Young Infants: For ſuch were the ſubjects of Circumciſion.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:37245:9"/>
            <p>5. And Laſtly, The Apoſtle repreſents the new Birth in theſe Scriptures, in which all the Elect, Young and Old, are as paſſive, as a Child is in its own natural birth, and this Spiritual birth is frequently ſet forth by ſprinkling, waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and pouring water, as I have proved; and let them prove that it is repreſented by dipping or plunging, if they can, in all the Book of God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Let us hear ſomething of what Mr. <hi>John Ollyffe,</hi> Rector of <hi>Almer,</hi> in the County of <hi>Dorſet,</hi> ſaith in his <hi>Brief Defence of Infant-Baptiſm,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Mode or Manner of Baptiſm.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Mr. <hi>O.</hi> ſaith in <hi>pag.</hi> 57. <hi>It is to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that whenever the Holy Ghoſt, in the New Teſtament, hath occaſion to mention the Act of Dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, it is never expreſſed by this word that ſignifieth to baptize, but by another which we have but four times in the New Teſtament, viz.</hi> Luke 16.24. John 13.26. Matth. 26.23. Rev. 19.13. <hi>But whenever the Act of Baptizing is expreſt, it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways expreſt by another word. The word Baptize is often uſed to ſignifie any kind of waſhing or cleanſing by water, by the application of water any way to the thing,</hi> Mark 7.4. The Phariſees eat not except they waſh. <hi>In the Greek it is,</hi> Except they be baptized. <hi>Again,</hi> Luke 11.38. The Phariſees marvelled that our Saviour had not firſt waſhed before dinner. <hi>In the Greek likewiſe it is,</hi> That he was not firſt baptized.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> In <hi>pag.</hi> 59. <hi>In thoſe Examples which ſeem to be moſt expreſs for Dipping, and therefore are moſt commonly urged for the Proof of it, there is at moſt but a bare probability of it, and hardly that in ſome; but there is no demonſtrative Proof can be made from any of them: The firſt is</hi> Mat. 3.13, 16. <hi>which ſets forth the Baptiſm of our Saviour by</hi> John
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:37245:9"/>Baptiſt <hi>at</hi> Jordan, <hi>ver.</hi> 16. Jeſus when he was baptized, went up ſtraitway out of the water, <hi>&amp;c. But indeed this Text, if rightly interpreted, doth not ſo much as prove that our Saviour went into the water at all; for in the Greek — he came up from the water, and not out of it,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And ſo I have it in my <hi>Spaniſt</hi> Teſtament alſo, <hi>viz. Y Jeſus Deſque Fue Baptizado Subio Luego Del Aqua, y heaqui los cielos le Fueron Abiertos: y vido Al Eſpiritu de Dios que Decendia, como paloma, y venia Sobre el:</hi> And Jeſus when he was baptized, came up ſtraightway from the water; <hi>Subio Luego Del Agua,</hi> came up from the water, and not out of the water.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>O.</hi> ſaith, <hi>Another Text that is urged is</hi> John 3.23. <hi>That</hi> John was baptizing in Enon near Salim, becauſe there was much water there: <hi>And becauſe of the numbers of thoſe that went to</hi> John <hi>to be baptized, it was moſt convenient that it ſhould be in ſuch places where there was plenty of water; but can any one prove hence that they were baptized by dipping into it, or under it,</hi> &amp;c.? <hi>In that place it is not ſaid, that there was much water together; but in the Original it is</hi> many waters, <hi>that is, many Streams or Rivulets,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>But let that be how it will, there is no determinate manner expreſt, or to be certainly and evidently concluded, as ought to have been, to build a Conſequence of ſuch a nature upon, as to infer an obligation to ſuch a determinate manner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus you hear what this Learned Author ſaith touching the Mode of Baptiſm, and it is to be obſerved from Mr. <hi>B. K</hi>'s. own words to me, in his Book, that this Mode of theirs is but a bare Suppoſition at beſt, becauſe, ſaith he, <hi>Suppoſe it be found at the Laſt Day to be Dipping.</hi> This looks little, eſpecially to lay ſuch a ſtreſs upon it, as to Aſſert all other Modes are no Baptiſm; for
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:37245:10"/>if he had a clear Command for it, why had he not ſaid, You ſhall find it to be Dipping at the Laſt Day, and not <hi>Suppoſe it be found ſo?</hi> But, ſay I, Suppoſe it be found at the Laſt Day to be Sprinkling, pouring Water, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For there is a far greater Probability of that, then of Dipping, as I have ſufficiently proved. Wherefore this Great, Pretended, Infallible Mode of Dipping for Baptiſm, is but a bare <hi>may be</hi> at the beſt.</p>
            <p>I ſhall deſcant a little upon the unſeemlineſs of Immerſion of Women and Maids in Baptiſm.</p>
            <p n="1">1. If it be a ſhame for a Woman to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered in the Church and Worſhip of God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the Angels, how much more abominable in the fight of God, Angels, and Men, is it for Women and Young Maids to be uncovered, by being ſtript out of their ordinary Dreſs within a little of naked, and to be handled about the Back and Breaſt, and have their Heels tript up, and flounced over Head and Ears for Baptiſm? This is againſt the plain written Word in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. For Baptiſm is a part of Goſpel Church-Worſhip.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Doth not Nature it ſelf teach us, that it is a ſhameful luxurious way thus to baptize Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and Maids: For though the Mans Hands do not ſlip, it is a thouſand to one but his Heart and Thoughts may; for I know of no Saint upon Earth, that is ſo perfectly holy, as to be out of the reach of Satans Temptations; for <hi>David,</hi> though a Man after Gods own Heart, was inſnar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the remote ſight of a beautiful <hi>Bathſheba</hi> a waſhing her ſelf, though he was not ſo near as to handle her.</p>
            <p n="3">3. All ſober modeſt Women do count it to be a very bold laſcivious Action for any Man, except their own Husband, to attempt to lay his Hands
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:37245:10"/>upon her Breaſts, and looks upon it to be but one degree ſhort of moſt notorious Impudence: And the Caution concerning Womens behaviour and deportment in the Church, and worſhip of God, is brought in by the Apoſtle Argumenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivily, <hi>viz. Becauſe of the Angels; for they are ſtrict obſervators of</hi> ALL <hi>perſons, in the Church and worſhip of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Chriſt hath forbid all wanton Looks, to prevent Luxury and Uncleanneſs; therefore he never appointed the Holy Ordinance of Baptiſm to run parallel in this muddy Channel with it, <hi>viz.</hi> For Women and young Maids to be made ſuch a ſhameful ſpectacle to Angels and Men, which is moſt abominable; for it is againſt the Law and Light of nature, as well as againſt the Expreſs Commands of God, namely, <hi>To abstain from all appearance of evil, and let all things be done decently, and in order.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Were we in a State of Innocency, ſuch a Mode of Baptiſm might be Authentick; but it can never be good in our depraved laps'd Eſtate, eſpecially if we conſider theſe Things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>(1.) There is no Saint of God, either Man or Woman, but is liable to Temptations.</item>
               <item>(2.) Satans great Work and Buſineſs lieth chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly among Chriſtians, to tempt them to ſin.</item>
               <item>(3.) That there are the Remainders of corrupt nature in all the Saints of God, whilſt they are in this Life.</item>
               <item>(4.) The greateſt Saint upon Earth hath a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful Heart within him, and that Soul that knows nothing of this, hath little acquaintance, either with God or his own heart; <hi>The heart is deceitful above all things, and deſperately wicked, who can know it?</hi> Jer. 17.9.</item>
            </list>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:37245:11"/>
            <p n="6">6. For a Man to go hand in hand with a beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful brisk young Gentlewoman, or Maid, into the water, and to handle her back and breaſts, and trip up her heels, and flounce her over head and ears, is a very immodeſt, tempting thing, becauſe there are as many Remainders of ſin in a Believer as there is in an old Sinner, only here lieth the difference, Sin doth not reign in a Believer.</p>
            <list>
               <item>(1.) Though the domineering power of ſin in the believer be deſtroyed, yet the being of ſin is not; for though it be not in him as a King, yet it is in him as a Tyrant.</item>
               <item>(2.) But ſin reigns over the ſinner, as the Heart of a believer is a Throne for Chriſt and Grace, ſo the Heart of a ſinner is a Throne for ſin and Satan.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="7">7. Theſe Men that Tranſact this Mode of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, muſt put great confidence in their own Hearts, otherwiſe they could never dare be ſo bold thus to dally with a Temptation: But what ſaith the Scripture, <hi>He that truſteth his own heart is a fool;</hi> and the reaſon is plain, becauſe it is ſo deceitful as nothing can be more; <hi>for it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitſul above all things, and deſperately wicked; who can know it?</hi> And this many a dear Child of God have found by woful experience; therefore it is every Chriſtians Duty to keep a ſtrict watch over his own heart, and againſt the Temptations of Satan, to keep them aſunder; for our Hearts are like Tinder, that no ſooner the Tempter ſtrikes Fire, but it takes, unleſs the Heart be well guarded.</p>
            <p n="8">8. By this unſeemly Mode of Baptiſm they go not only into the water, but at the ſame time they run into the Fire of Temptation, and dally with the Tempter; wherefore I will appeal to
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:37245:11"/>theſe Mens own Hearts and Conſciences, that ingage in this Mode, whether they can perform this Thing, with thoſe Female Subjects aforeſaid, without being tempted by Satan to vain laſcivious Thoughts. Pray remember to watch and obſerve your Hearts the next time, if ever you ingage in it again, and if you do, I am ſure you will find what I ſay to be true. But in the baptizing the Infant Seed of Believers, by ſprinkling water upon them, there is none of all this danger, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is no Object to draw out the Hearts Luſts for Satan to faſten his Temptation upon; therefore Dipping or Immerſion for Baptiſm cannot be good.</p>
            <p n="9">9. The Words for Adminiſtration of the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of Baptiſm ought to be uſed at the ſame Inſtant when the water is applied to the Perſon baptized; but if Dipping or Plunging be the Mode of Baptiſm, then theſe things would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily follow:</p>
            <p n="1">1. They muſt go into the water very near as deep as their Waſte, before the words of Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration are ſpoken, and ſo they are half baptized before the words are ſpoken.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If the words are ſpoken before their heels are tript up, then they are baptized before they are dipped.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And Laſtly, If they ſpeak the words while they have them under water, they cannot be active in their own Baptiſm, which is to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw one of their own grand Arguments they produce to prove that none but Adult Believers ought to be baptized, <hi>viz. Becauſe that all Perſons ought to be Active in their own Baptiſm.</hi> Pray what Grace can they exerciſe under Water, when they can ſcarcely exerciſe their Reaſon, much leſs their Graces.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:37245:12"/>
            <p n="10">10. Saith Mr. <hi>K. pag.</hi> 6. <hi>Sir, you ſhould take more heed to your Words, and to what you Aſſert: Is it ſaid they were baptized in the Jaylors houſe,</hi> &amp;c.?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>How can you ſay</hi> pag. 7. <hi>that they were all bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized in his own houſe, when the Text ſpeaks not any ſuch thing? How can you preſume to Aſſert, that they did not go out of the Houſe? Reader, obſerve the Text well.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo ſay I too: Pray, Reader, obſerve the Text well; and therefore I will fairly repeat it in <hi>Acts</hi> 16.23.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And when they had laid many ſtripes upon them, they caſt them into priſon; charging the jaylor to keep them ſafely.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ver. 24. <hi>Who having received ſuch a charge, thruſt them into the inner priſon, and made their feet faſt in the ſtocks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ver. 25. <hi>And at midnight Paul and Silas pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſang praiſes unto God, and the priſoners heard them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ver. 26. <hi>And ſuddenly there was a great earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake, ſo that the foundations of the priſon were ſhaken: and immediately all the doors were opened, and every ones bands were looſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ver. 27. <hi>And the keeper of the priſon awaking out of his ſleep, and ſeeing the priſon doors open, he drew out his ſword, and would have killed himſelf, ſuppoſing that the priſoners had been fled.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ver. 28. <hi>But Paul cried with a loud voice, ſaying, Do thy ſelf no harm; for we are all here.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From this Paſſage we may obſerve, that the Jailors Houſe or Appartment, and the Place of <hi>Paul</hi>'s cloſe confinement, were both within view, and call one of another; for <hi>Paul</hi> perceiving that the Jaylor would have murdered himſelf, crys out unto him to prevent it.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:37245:12"/>
            <p>Ver. 29. <hi>Then he called for a light, and ſprang in, and came trembling, and fell down before Paul and Silas;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ver. 30. <hi>And brought them out, and ſaid, Sirs, what muſt I do to be ſaved?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This ſeems as if that Inner Priſon, where they were thruſt, was a dark Dungeon, becauſe the Jaylor called for a Light, and ſprang in, and brought them out of it, and not out of the Houſe; for then they preached the Word of God to him, and to all that were in his Houſe, as you may ſee in <hi>Verſe</hi> 32.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And they ſpake unto him the word of the Lord, and to all that were in his houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus you ſee they were not out of the Houſe, which I look upon to be the Jail-keepers Appart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; for they preached to all that were in it.</p>
            <p>But ſaith Mr. <hi>K. Might they not in that hour go a little way out of the Houſe, and be baptized?</hi> This is begging the Queſtion, and yet he thus concludes, <hi>viz. 'Tis evident he abuſes the Sacred Text.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But hitherto you may ſee it is plain they did not go out of the Houſe.</p>
            <p>Ver. 33. <hi>And he took them the ſame hour of the night, and waſhed their ſtripes; and was baptized, he and all his, ſtraightway.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ver. 34. <hi>And when he had brought them into his houſe, he ſet meat before them, and they rejoiced, believing in God with all his houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This was to bring them into ſome more pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar Place, or Dining-Room in his Houſe; for you ſee it is clear, they were not out of the Priſon before; for ſo it appears by the next <hi>Verſe,</hi> viz.</p>
            <p>Ver. 35. <hi>And when it was day, the magiſtrates ſent the ſergeants, ſaying, Let thoſe men go.</hi> But the Apoſtles refuſed to go out of the Priſon, <hi>And
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:37245:13"/>they came and beſought them, and deſired them to depart out of the city.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus you ſee here was (1.) The Jaylors bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Apoſtles out of their cloſe confinement, after his conviction: (2.) There was preaching the Word of the Lord to all that were in his Houſe, and not out of his Houſe: (3.) Here was waſhing their ſtripes after they were taken out of their cloſe confinement into his Houſe at large: (4.) And Laſtly, Here was their Baptiſm: And all this was done in the ſame hour of the Night, ſtraightway; and then when this was done, he invites them into his own peculiar Appartment, or Dining-Room, and ſet Meat before them. And in the laſt place, it doth plainly appear, that they did not go out of the Houſe, or Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, all night, becauſe they were there in the Morning, and refuſed to go out when the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates ſent to the Jaylor to releaſe them; therefore there is no manner of ground to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, that they went out of the Priſon, and out of the City, a little way in the Night to be baptized in a River or a Pond of Water; but beſides, the Gates of Cities uſe to be ſhut in the Night, and Guard kept at them, who would have ſecured them, had they attempted to go out in the night; <hi>Ergo,</hi> they were baptized in the Houſe. So that I have not abuſed the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Text; but it is evident, that Mr. <hi>K.</hi> hath abuſed me in charging me falſely.</p>
            <p n="12">12. And Laſtly, I ſhall give ſome Reaſons to Evince that the Face of the Subject is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pereſt part to be baptized, Becauſe by the Face both God and Man are deſcribed.</p>
            <p n="1">1. God is deſcribed by his <hi>moſt glorious face, Pſal.</hi> 51.9. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 44.24. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 18.10. Not that we are to conceive of God as of any Form or
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:37245:13"/>Shape, who is a moſt Glorious, Immenſe, Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Being in himſelf; but it is in condeſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to our weak capacities.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Man is deſcribed and beſt known by the Face, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.22. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.9. And how com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon a thing is it among Men to ſay, I never ſaw ſuch an Ones Face? That is, they never ſaw the Perſon.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Face is the propereſt part for the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of water in Baptiſm, becauſe the Face repreſents the whole Man.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Face ought to be baptized as the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pereſt part, becauſe the part baptized ought to be naked, for theſe Reaſons, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>(1.) Becauſe otherwiſe the Cloaths, and not the Perſon, are baptized.</p>
            <p>(2.) Becauſe it maketh the trueſt Figure of Man in his natural laps'd State, before he is waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Water of Regeneration, and renewed by the Holy Ghoſt, by which the Soul puts on theſe two bleſſed Garments of Salvation, namely, Chriſts Righteouſneſs for Juſtification, and the Robe of Holineſs for Sanctification. Every Soul in a laps'd State, you have ſet forth, in theſe two Texts, in the <hi>old</hi> and <hi>New Teſtament;</hi> firſt in the <hi>Old Teſtament, Ezek.</hi> 16.4, 5, 6. Here you have Man in his natural State, which is, unſavoury, loathſome, polluted and helpleſs; and in the <hi>New Teſtament, Rev.</hi> 3. there he is ſet forth to be wretched, and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and poor, and blind, and naked: This is the State and Condition of all Men by nature, before they are waſhed in Regeneration.</p>
            <p n="4">4. And Laſtly, The Face of the Subject is the propereſt part for the application of water in Baptiſm, becauſe Nature it ſelf teacheth us, that the Face is the moſt delightful, comely part of Man for Converſation: We do not care to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:37245:14"/>converſe with a Man that turns his back upon us. Thus much for the part of the Subject that ought to be baptized, and the poſture the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject ought to be prepared in, and that is the naked Face.</p>
            <p>Thus I have confuted Mr. <hi>Keach</hi>'s Arguments, which he hath produced to prove that Dipping is the only Infallible Mode for Baptiſm, whereas there is neither Precept nor Example for it; no, not ſo much as a bare <hi>May be</hi> for it in all the Book of God; but you ſee there is a great Analogy between thoſe many Sprinklings and Baptiſm, though the Mode is not abſolutely determined declaratively.</p>
            <p>II. I will prove that all Elect dying Infants muſt have the Grace of Faith, or they can never be ſaved.</p>
            <p n="1">1. But ſaith Mr. <hi>K.</hi> in <hi>p.</hi> 14, 16. <hi>How doth God ſanctifie dying Infants? I ſpeak as to the Mode of it: No mortal Man I am ſure can tell; if it is by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing Grace, let it be ſo, though it can't be proved while the World ſtands, yet Gods deſign therein could not be the ſame in them as in others,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Though the Grace is given, by which we do believe, yet is not the Act ours? Can God be ſaid to believe for us, or can there be Faith in any Subject, and yet no knowledge of the Object?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, that the Mode of ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying Elect dying Infants muſt be by Infuſion of Grace by the Holy Spirit into their Souls, is as clear as the Sun, becauſe there is no other way for Old or Young to be ſavingly ſanctified by. 2. God hath promiſed it, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 44.3. <hi>I will pour my ſpirit upon thy ſeed, and my bleſſing upon thine off-ſpring,</hi> &amp;c. 3. Gods deſign is the ſame in the infuſing Grace and Holineſs into an Elect Infant,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:37245:14"/>as it is in an Adult Elect Sinner; for God hath no other End, nor higher Deſign, then the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifying his own Free Grace in the ſalvation of both Old and Young; therefore that part of your carnal Argument is already deſtroyed. Pray, Sir, in your next let us know if God hath any other, or differing Deſign or End, in the ſaving Adult Elect Sinners, from that of ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying and ſaving Elect dying Infants; and let us alſo know what way that is.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Faith is the Gift of God, though the Act of Faith may be ſaid to be the Believers, yet if God do not Act in the Believers Faith, his Act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing will ſignifie nothing; for God <hi>is the authour and finiſher of our faith, Heb.</hi> 12. And <hi>it is God that worketh in us, both the will and the deed of his good pleaſure,</hi> Phil. 2.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Though the Act of Faith may be ſaid to be the Believers, yet the Habit of Faith is Gods; for the Believer is wholly paſſive in the reception of Grace, and there muſt be Habits before there can be Acts; there muſt be the Root of Grace before there can be the Fruit of Grace; and a young Infant is as capable of receiving the Habits of Grace, wherein the Subjects are wholly paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive, as an Adult Perſon is.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> could never have leaped in his Mothers Womb for joy, had he not known God in Chriſt, the only true Object of Joy.</p>
            <p>Sir, You have meaſured theſe Profound My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries by the Rule of carnal Reaſon, which is a very falſe Rule to meaſure it by: The Faith of God doth not ſtand in the Wiſdom of Men.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Saith Mr. <hi>K.</hi> in <hi>p.</hi> 14. <hi>We ſay the ſame thing with worthy Mr.</hi> Marſhal, <hi>in</hi> pag. 78. <hi>of his Book, which you recited in the</hi> 24th. pag. <hi>of yours,</hi> viz. <hi>That <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion betwixt Chriſt and the Soul is fully ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:37245:15"/>by Chriſt, giving the Spirit of Faith to us, even before we can Act Faith in the reception of Him, becauſe by this Grace, or Spirit of Faith, the Soul is inclined to an active receiving of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pray Mr. <hi>K.</hi> did worthy Mr. <hi>Marſhal</hi> ſay no more? If he did, how dare you be ſo unjuſt, to deal thus unfairly by Mr. <hi>Marſhal,</hi> as to leave out the concluſion of his Sentence, without an <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as if he had ſaid no more? Pray Reader, look into the <hi>Pages</hi> Mr. <hi>K.</hi> hath quoted, both of Mr. <hi>Marſhal</hi>'s Book and mine, and there you will find the concluſion of his Sentence thus, <hi>viz. And no doubt Chriſt is thus united to many In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, which have the Spirit of Faith, becauſe they are not come to the years of underſtanding.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is this to ſay the ſame thing with worthy Mr. <hi>Marſhal?</hi> But this is as true, as that I ſpent 20 Leaves in my former Book, to prove that which No body denies. But pray what hath Mr. <hi>Marſhal</hi> ſaid in this, to deſtroy or enervate the Notion of Habitual Faith, in Elect dying Infants? For though he hath not uſed the very ſame Words, yet it is to the ſame effect, and carrieth an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quivalent in it, with that of Habitual Faith. Now if Mr. <hi>K.</hi> ſaith the ſame thing with worthy Mr. <hi>Marſhal,</hi> then Mr. <hi>K.</hi> and I am agreed.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Saith Mr. <hi>K. Is Regeneration in your Infants, that are Regenerated, the Fruit or Product of this Spirit of Faith, or Habits which you plead for, to be infuſed into them when Infants? Sure if they had any ſuch Habits, when Infants, they need no other inſpired Habits, when they are grown up.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where the Habits and Principles of Grace are once infuſed into a Soul, they can never be loſt, neither ſhall they need any other inſpired Habits of Grace, when they are grown Perſons; for where theſe Habits are once planted, they can
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:37245:15"/>never be deſtroyed; for once in Chriſt by Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, and for ever in Chriſt by Juſtification and Sanctification; for that Soul is in a State of Grace, and hath the Life of Chriſt in him, and that Life can never be loſt, becauſe it is in Chriſt the Son of God; it is in the keeping of Chriſt, and therefore, to ſpeak with Reverence, Chriſt himſelf may as ſoon be loſt as that.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We may conclude, that many children of Believers, that did not die in their Infancy, have had the Habits of Grace infuſed into their Souls in their Infancy, and that may be the reaſon, why ſo many of them, when they are grown Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, can tell they have Grace, but know not how, nor when, they came by it. No doubt <hi>Timothy</hi> had Grace infuſed into him in his Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, becauſe we read not any thing of his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, no more than we do of his Baptiſm, wherefore both might be effected in his Infancy, being the Son of a godly Mother: But the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <hi>Paul</hi> could tell the time of his own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, and alſo his Baptiſm, <hi>Acts</hi> 9.</p>
            <p n="3">3. All Infants are conceived in ſin, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.5. There are all the Habits or Seeds of ſin in an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant, in its firſt Conception or Formation, even as many as there are in an Adult Sinner; <hi>for all have ſinned, and come ſhort of the glory of God;</hi> therefore Elect dying Infants muſt be regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, they muſt be begotten and born of God; for God will be a reconciled Father to none but them which he ſpiritually begets; for God was in Chriſt, reconciling the World to himſelf, not imputing their Treſpaſſes unto them. Thus you ſee, as young Infants are brought into the ſame Ballance of Original Guilt and Pollution with Adult old Sinners, ſo they muſt be brought into the ſame Ballance of Juſtification, Adoption and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:37245:16"/>Sanctification with Elect Adult Believers, or they can never be ſaved.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Mr. <hi>K.</hi> doth own, That <hi>all Infants are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the guilt and ſtain of Original Sin by Nature;</hi> And he alſo ſaith, <hi>We do believe, that all thoſe dying Infants who are ſaved, God doth in ſome way or another, which is not known to us, ſanctifie them; for no unclean thing can enter into the Heavenly Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is no other way but this, <hi>viz.</hi> Children muſt be juſtified, and acquitted from the guilt of Original Sin; And, <hi>ſecondly,</hi> they muſt be ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified and cleanſed from the filth and pollution of ſin; they muſt be regenerated and made Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the Divine Nature, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4. For without Holineſs no Man ſhall ſee the Lord: The Fallen Angels may as well expect to be ſaved as any unregenerate Soul may, either Old or Young, that dyeth in that State and Condition.</p>
            <p n="2">2. All Children are elected and choſen of God, that are ſaved dying in their Infancy, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they muſt have the Grace of Faith to unite them to Chriſt, which is the Faith that is pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar to Gods Elect, <hi>Titus</hi> 1.1. For all Mankind by Nature are in a ſtate of Unbelief; for it was that Sin that brought Man into a State of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation; for had our firſt Parents believed God, when he told them, if they eat of the <hi>Tree of Knowledge of Good and Evil</hi> they ſhould die, Man had never fell into a State of Sin and Condemnation. Now the oppoſite Grace to the Sin of Unbelief is Faith, and Habitual Faith by the powerful Agency of the bleſſed Spirit of Grace, is ſufficient to ſubdue and conquer origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Unbelief, and to juſtifie and ſanctifie them by the application of the Righteouſneſs, Blood, and Merits of Jeſus Chriſt to their Souls. It is
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:37245:16"/>not Man's acting Faith that juſtifies him, but it is the Habit of Faith in the Righteouſneſs of Jeſus Chriſt that doth that. The Act of Faith in a ſenſe, may be ſaid to be the Creatures, but the Habit of Faith is Gods own Free Act in the Creature; wherefore if Man cannot be juſtified without his acting of Grace, then Juſtification depends on the Acting of the Creature: Though a Believer may be ſaid to have a hand in his own Sanctification, yet he hath none at all in his Juſtification.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The State of a young Child by Nature is as much depraved by the Fall of <hi>Adam,</hi> as the oldeſt Sinner upon Earth; therefore it muſt be by the very ſame Grace for kind, though it may not be for degree, that muſt juſtifie, ſanctifie, and ſave a young Infant dying in his Infancy, as is to juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, ſanctifie, and ſave an Elect Adult Believer, and that is by Faith; <hi>For by grace are ye ſaved, through faith, and that not of your ſelves, it is the gift of God.</hi> Now is not a young Babe in the Womb, or Cradle, as capable of this Salvation as the oldeſt Saint upon Earth? And is there any other way for the ſaving of any, either old or young, but this, <hi>Even the righteouſneſs of God which is by Faith of Jeſus Chriſt unto all, and upon all them that believe; for there is no difference: For all have ſinned, and come ſhort of the glory of God; Being juſtified freely by his grace, through the redemption that is in Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> Rom. 3.</p>
            <p n="4">4. And Laſtly, Young Infants that die in their Infancy, muſt have the Image of God reſtored unto them, and enſtamped upon them, which was blotted out by the Fall of <hi>Adam,</hi> or they can never be ſaved, and that muſt be by Infu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Grace and Holineſs into their Souls, and ſo make them partakers of the Divine Nature,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:37245:17"/>which is the new Creation in the Soul; and the new Creature muſt have all his Lineaments, or elſe the new Creature would be imperfect; it muſt have Eyes, or elſe it would be blind, and Faith is the new Creatures Eyes, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. To conclude, The Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, and Faith in the juſtifying, ſanctifying, and ſaving a Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, ever goeth together; therefore none can be ſaved by the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Grace or Spirit of Faith; for they are all brought into the Ballance of Redemption to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30. <hi>But of him are ye in Chriſt Jeſus, who of God is made unto us wiſdom, and righteouſneſs, and ſanctification, and redemption.</hi> Now where is that differing way, or many ways for the ſaving Elect dying Infants, from that of ſanctifying and ſaving Elect old Sinners? Mr. <hi>K.</hi> ſaith in his <hi>Title Page,</hi> that I am an unskil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Perſon in <hi>Polemical Cures;</hi> but I am ſure, thoſe that Aſſert, That there are more ways than one for the ſanctifying and ſaving young Infants, differing from that of Adult Believers, are very unskilful Phyſicians; and I pitty thoſe poor Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that have no skilfuller Phyſicians than theſe are, to take care of them.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Mr. <hi>K.</hi> brings in a Caution by way of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, <hi>viz.</hi> Saith he, <hi>'Tis forbid, and a ſinful thing, for any to pry into Gods Secret. All they that pry into the way how God applies the Merits of Chriſt to dying Infants, and ſanctifies them, do pry into Gods Secrets,</hi> Ergo.</p>
            <p>But thoſe things which are revealed belong un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us, and to our Children for ever. The juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying, ſanctifying, and ſaving all the Elect of God, is a revealed thing, as I have ſufficiently proved, therefore it is not a ſinful thing to pry into the way how God applies the Merits of
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:37245:17"/>Chriſt to dying Infants, and ſanctifie them. This is like the P. that forbids the <hi>Laicks</hi> the uſe of the <hi>Bible,</hi> becauſe they ſhould not detect their Errours and falſe Doctrines.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Scripture hath revealed unto us, that we are all Children of wrath by nature, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.3. and conceived in ſin, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.5. Here is our <hi>Epidemical Malady</hi> revealed.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Here is alſo the <hi>Remedy</hi> revealed, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. <hi>For there is one God, and one mediatour between God and man, the man Chriſt Jeſus; who gave himſelf a ranſom for all;</hi> that is, eſpecially for all the Elect, and if ſo, then Chriſt died as much for all Elect dying Infants, as for all Elect old Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; <hi>Acts</hi> 4.12. <hi>Neither is there ſalvation in any other: for there is none other name under heaven gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven among men whereby we muſt be ſaved.</hi> Eph. 4. <hi>One Lord, one faith, one baptiſm, One God and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of all, who is above all, and through all, and in you all.</hi> And this one Faith is the Faith of Gods Elect, <hi>Titus</hi> 1.1. And by this Faith they ſhall get the Victory, becauſe they are born of God, Children of the moſt High, Heirs of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, made meet to partake of the Inheritance with the Saints in Light. Thus you ſee this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Implicite Faith overthrown, and your Argument againſt prying into the way of Gods ſanctifying and ſaving Elect dying Infants de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>O but</hi> (ſaith Mr. <hi>K.</hi> in <hi>pag.</hi> 3.) <hi>I hope his Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Paſtor, whom I have more cauſe both to love and honour, than Ten Thouſand Inſtructors in Chriſt, he being the bleſſed Inſtrument in my Converſion al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Fourty Years agoe, gave no encouragement to him thus to write and abuſe his Brethren.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But my Reverend Paſtor, who is worthy of double honour, he never taught you any ſuch
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:37245:18"/>kind of Doctrine; for though he might be an Inſtrument in Gods Hand of making you a <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian,</hi> yet he never had any hand in making you an <hi>Anabaptiſt,</hi> neither is he a Perſon of ſuch a weak Capacity, as not to ſee through, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond your little kind of Inſinuations and Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, by which you endeavour to ingage him to ſide with you, and juſtifie your corrupt Doctrines and Principles, in oppoſition to his own; but that will not do.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Saith Mr. <hi>K. Little Children may have Faith, if God pleaſe to work a Miracle, and inſpire them with his Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I Anſwer, All that Faith that is in a Soul, that is not wrought by a miraculous Power, is no better than the Faith of Fallen Angels, <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.19. <hi>Thou believeſt that there is one God; thou doeſt well: the devils alſo believe, and tremble.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. It is no leſs a Miracle to work Faith in a dead Sinner, in raiſing him from the Grave of Unbelief, then it was to raiſe a dead crucified Saviour, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.19, 20. <hi>And what is the exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing greatneſs of his power to us ward who believe, according to the working of his mighty power; Which he wrought in Chriſt when he raiſed him from the dead, and ſet him at his own right hand in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly places.</hi> It was always counted a Miracle to raiſe the Dead: <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.1. <hi>And you hath he quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned who were dead in treſpaſſes and ſins.</hi> What is become of this carnal unbelieving Propoſition?</p>
            <p n="6">6. And Laſtly, Saith Mr. <hi>B. K. If Children be part of their Parents, then certainly if the Parents go to Heaven, all their Children muſt likewiſe; for the whole of Believers ſhall be ſaved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Argument, like the former, is lighter than Vanity. It doth not follow, that becauſe I am a Believer, and my Children a part of me,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:37245:18"/>they ſhall therefore be ſaved: But yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, the Children of Believers have a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar Priviledge above all other Mens Children in the World; and if you ask me, what Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that is, I muſt refer you to the Apoſtles for Anſwer, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.39. and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14. Here you ſee all the Children of believing Parents are holy Children; nay, if there be but one of their Parents that is a Believer, it intituleth them to this Great Honour and Priviledge of being holy Children.</p>
            <p n="2">2. All the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were called <hi>holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs unto the Lord,</hi> Jer. 2.3. And they are called Gods Son, in <hi>Exod.</hi> 4. <hi>And thou ſhalt ſay unto Pharaoh, Thus ſaith the Lord, Iſrael is my ſon, even my firſt born. And I ſay unto thee, Let my ſon go,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Here you ſee all <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as one Man, are called Gods Son, and Holineſs to the Lord alſo, and yet it is no breach of Charity to conclude, that all <hi>Iſrael</hi> were not ſaved, though they were all a part one of another, as Members of one Body are; ſo neither will all the Children of Believers be ſaved, though they are a part of their believing Parents, as Members of a Body are, and called holy Children: So that this Argument is clearly pluckt up by the Roots.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee I have clearly proved, that there is no Juſtification, nor Sanctification, nor Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation for dying Infants; without the Grace, Habit, or Spirit of Faith, and alſo, that there is but one way of ſanctifying and ſaving all the Elect of God, both Old and Young; therefore all the Arguments, which are raiſed againſt it, are utterly deſtroyed.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:37245:19"/>
            <p>III. In the third place I will prove, that the Covenant which God made with <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed, in <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. was but one Covenant, and that it was the ſame God made with <hi>Adam</hi> after the Fall, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. and with <hi>Noah</hi> after the Flood, <hi>Gen.</hi> 9. And it is the ſame now, and all Believers and all their Seed, both Spiritual and Carnal, are in it, in the full ſubſtantial Latitude of it, notwithſtanding all that can be ſaid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it.</p>
            <p>But ſaith Mr. <hi>K.</hi> in <hi>pag.</hi> 23. <hi>'Tis evident there was two Covenants contained in thoſe Tranſactings of God with</hi> Abraham, <hi>one peculiar reſpecting onely his natural Seed, or Off-ſpring, as ſuch; for the Covenant of Grace promiſed to him, did not pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarly relate to</hi> Abraham's <hi>Natural Seed that were Elected Perſons, but to all the Gentiles alſo, who believed in Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. There is no ſuch declared diſtinction in the Covenant God made with <hi>Abraham,</hi> in <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.2, 7. For though the Elect <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> are principally intended, yet all the Seed of Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, both Spiritual and Carnal, are included, and ought to partake of the External Benefits and Bleſſings thereof. But it may be objected, The Seed of believing <hi>Gentiles</hi> are not to be cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed, neither have they a Right to the <hi>Land of Canaan,</hi> therefore they cannot be in <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Covenant. Pray what Part or Lot had the Seed of <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Noah</hi> in either of theſe, and yet they were in the ſame Covenant which God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed and ratified with <hi>Abraham?</hi> Nay, Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of the Seed of <hi>Abraham</hi> never ſaw the <hi>Land of Canaan;</hi> for the Seed of <hi>Abraham</hi> were not poſſeſſed of that till 430. Years after the Covenant was made with <hi>Abraham, Gal.</hi> 3.17.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:37245:19"/>
            <p n="2">2. The Covenant which God made with <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> was out one, and that is an Everlaſting Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant; but if it had been two, it ſhould have been Everlaſting Covenants; therefore I will lay down the Terms of it fairly, and let us ſee if any ſuch Deduction can be made, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.2, 7, 10, 11. <hi>And I will make my covenant between me and thee, and will multiply thee exceedingly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And I will eſtabliſh my covenant between me and thee, and thy ſeed after thee, in their generations, for an everlaſting covenant; to be a God unto thee, and to thy ſeed after thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is my covenant, which ye ſhall keep between me, and you, and thy ſeed after thee; Every man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>child among you ſhall be cirunmciſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And ye ſhall circumciſe the fleſh of your fore-skin, and it ſhall be a token of the covenant betwixt me and you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here you ſee it is but one Covenant, and Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion is only the Token thereof, but not the Covenant.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Saith Mr. <hi>K.</hi> in <hi>pag.</hi> 25. <hi>Obſerve alſo, that as theſe things peculiarly appertained to his Natural Seed as ſuch, ſo Circumciſion is expreſly called Gods Covenant,</hi> Gen. 17.</p>
            <p>If this be ſo, then <hi>Iſhmael</hi> was in the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and yet Mr. <hi>K.</hi> doth own in his Book, that <hi>Iſhmael</hi> was not in the Covenant, nor his Seed; but if Circumciſion be the Covenant, then he was in it, becauſe he was circumciſed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.20, 21, 23. So that this Text, with his own Argument, do utterly deſtroy that Notion of his, That there were Two Covenants made with <hi>Abraham,</hi> and that one of them was Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, becauſe then <hi>Iſhmael</hi> muſt have been in it. Indeed it is expreſly called the Token of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, but it is no where expreſly called the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:37245:20"/>Covenant in all the Holy Scriptures, as I know of, and if it be, he ſhould have done well to have cited it, that others might have ſeen it, as well as himſelf.</p>
            <p>Thus having premiſed theſe things, I ſhall proceed.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In the firſt place I will begin with that Text in <hi>Acts</hi> 2.39. <hi>For the promiſe is unto you, and to your children, and to all that are afar off, even as many as the Lord our God ſhall call.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here in the firſt part of this Verſe, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle informs theſe <hi>Jews,</hi> that had a hand in crucifying our Saviour, of their Covenant Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge, and their Children alſo; for the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe which the Apoſtle here ſpeaks of, that did belong to them and their Children, is no other then that which God made with <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed; therefore the Covenant was not repealed at the coming in of the Goſpel, nor diſſolved like an old uſeleſs Act of Parliament, neither were it two Covenants.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If we mind the latter part of the Verſe, we ſhall find, that whatever the Extent of that Promiſe was to the <hi>Jews,</hi> and all their Children, it is the ſame to all believing <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and all their Children; for it is not ſaid, To you <hi>Jews,</hi> and your Children, and to as many Adult <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,</hi> which are afar off, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> No; but the latter part of the Verſe is an exact Counterpane to the former part thereof; ſo that whatever the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe was to the <hi>Jews,</hi> and all their Children, is the ſame to all believing <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; for the latter part of the Verſe is to be meaſured by the former part thereof.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This Promiſe is Chriſt, who was firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared and promiſed unto <hi>Adam,</hi> and his Seed, in the new Covenant God made with him, when
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:37245:20"/>the old one was broken, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. Which Promiſe, or Covenant, hath been a Standing-Diſh for Believers, and all their Seed, to feed upon in all Ages, and ever will be while the World ſtands.</p>
            <p n="3">3. There ever hath, and ever will be a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Entail in this Covenant, unto all Believers and their Seed, from Generation to Generation, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 105.8. <hi>He hath remembred his covenant for ever, the word which he commanded to a thouſand generations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It runs in a Line from Parents to Children, until any of them ſinned themſelves out of it perſonally, as <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Judas,</hi> and Multitudes of the <hi>Jews</hi> did; for the Covenant of Grace conſiſts of two parts, an Inner Court and an Outer Court: So it was under the Law, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 8.16. And ſo it is under the Goſpel, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.1, 2. And it hath Internal and External Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, or Worſhippers, in it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.17. <hi>John</hi> 15.1, 2. And there are Spiritual and Temporal Bleſſings and Priviledges belong unto it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.1, 2. <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.33.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In the ſecond place, let us take a View of the Lineal Deſcent of the Covenant of Grace, <hi>viz.</hi> After our firſt Parents fell into a State of Sin and Miſery, by which the firſt Covenant was broken, namely, that of Works, then God made a Second or New Covenant with <hi>Adam,</hi> and his Seed, the Covenant of Grace in <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. But <hi>Cain</hi> ſinned himſelf out of it, and God Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated him with a Curſe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.10, 11, 13, 14. And God gave <hi>Adam Seth</hi> in the room of <hi>Abel</hi> whom <hi>Cain</hi> ſlew, <hi>ver.</hi> 25, 26.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Covenant of Grace continued from <hi>Adam</hi> to <hi>Noah,</hi> a Preacher of Righteouſneſs, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5. that is, he was a Goſpel Preacher;
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:37245:21"/>for he preached the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt for Juſtification and Salvation, and God confirmed and ratified the Covenant with <hi>Noah,</hi> and his Seed, before the Flood, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.18. <hi>But with thee will I eſtabliſh my covenant: and thou ſhalt come into the ark; thou, and thy ſons, and thy wife, and thy ſons wives with thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now was not this diſtinguiſhing peculiar Love and Grace, that God ſhould ſpare and preſerve <hi>Noah</hi> and all his Houſe, when all the reſt of the World were drowned, and utterly deſtroyed? Therefore they were in the Covenant of Grace.</p>
            <p n="2">2. God renewed his Covenant with <hi>Noah,</hi> and all his Seed, after the Flood, <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.9. <hi>And I, behold, I eſtabliſh my covenant with you, and with your ſeed after you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And we have the Token of the Covenant in the 12 and 13 Verſes, <hi>And God ſaid, This is the token of the covenant which I make between me, and you, and every living creature that is with you, for perpetual generations:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I do ſet my bow in the cloud, and it ſhall be for a token of a covenant between me and the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. This Covenant was principally made with <hi>Noah</hi> and his Seed, and conſiſted of ſpecial and common Mercies, both to Man and Beaſt. 2. The Token of this Covenant is extended to all, good and bad, Saints and Sinners, but chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and principally it is for God himſelf to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member his Covenant, <hi>Verſe</hi> 16. <hi>And the bow ſhall be in the cloud; and I will look upon it, that I may remember the everlaſting covenant,</hi> &amp;c. The Rain-bow is a Token that God will never deſtroy the World by Water again, as in <hi>ver.</hi> 11, 12, 13. and that Token remains as a Witneſs unto this Day. In which Token we may ſee the Goodneſs, and alſo Severity of God; Goodneſs to <hi>Noah</hi> and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:37245:21"/>his Family, which is extended unto us; for had <hi>Noah</hi> and his Family been drowned alſo, we had never been; and Severity againſt ſin, in that he deſtroyed all the ungodly World.</p>
            <p>From hence I ſhall make ſome Obſervations.</p>
            <p n="1">1. If the Token of that Covenant had diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appeared at the coming in of the Goſpel, in its Splendor and full Latitude, it might have been concluded, that the Covenant God made with <hi>Noah</hi> and <hi>Abraham</hi> had been Repealed and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, and ſo the Infant Seed of Believers caſt out, and in no Covenant at all; for that was the Token of the Covenant in the largeſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, both with a reſpect to God and Man: For if we do but obſerve the Terms and Tenure of the Covenant God made with <hi>Noah,</hi> before the Flood, and after the Flood, it is much the ſame, with a reſpect to <hi>Noah</hi> and his Family; and ſo likewiſe with <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Covenant, to him and his Seed; wherefore let us compare them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and alſo the Tokens, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.18. <hi>But with thee will I eſtabliſh my covenant: and thou ſhalt come into the ark,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Gen. 9.9. <hi>And I, behold, I eſtabliſh my cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with you, and with your ſeed after you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Covenant runs thus, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. <hi>And I will eſtabliſh my covenant between me and thee, and thy ſeed after thee,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For the Tokens of the Covenant, <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.12. <hi>And God ſaid, This is the token of the covenant which I make between me, and you, and every living creature that is with you, for perpetual generations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Gen. 17. <hi>And I will eſtabliſh my covenant be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween me and thee, and thy ſeed after thee, in their generations,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And ye ſhall circumciſe the fleſh of your fore-skin,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:37245:22"/>and it ſhall be a token of the covenant betwixt me and you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mark, that of <hi>Noah</hi>'s Covenant is called <hi>The Token;</hi> but this of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Covenant is called <hi>A Token.</hi> The firſt might be called <hi>The Token,</hi> becauſe it was to have no Succeſſor; and that of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s might be called <hi>A Token,</hi> becauſe it was to have a Succeſſor, namely Baptiſm; for the Token of <hi>Noah</hi>'s Covenant is to perpetual Generations, but ſo is not Circumciſion it ſelf, though it is ſaid in <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. <hi>And my covenant ſhall be in your fleſh, for an everlaſting covenant.</hi> So that when Circumciſion was aboliſhed the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant remained in the fleſh, therefore Baptiſm ſucceeded Circumciſion; for no Ordinances but them two have to do with the Fleſh in the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, in Initiation, as Circumciſion had, and Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm hath. Thus you ſee the Analogy there was between the Covenant and the Tokens thereof, God made with <hi>Noah</hi> and <hi>Abraham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Let us bring this Covenant God made with <hi>Noah,</hi> and <hi>Abraham,</hi> down into Goſpel-Times.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Let us obſerve what that Goſpel-Prophet ſaith, in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.8. <hi>In a little wrath I hid my face from thee, for a moment; but with everlaſting kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs will I have mercy on thee, ſaith the Lord thy redeemer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ver. 9. <hi>For this is as the waters of Noah unto me: for as I have ſworn that the waters of Noah ſhould no more go over the earth; ſo have I ſworn that I would not be wroth with thee, nor rebuke thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ver. 10. <hi>For the mountains ſhall depart, and the hills be removed, but my kindneſs ſhall not depart from thee, neither ſhall the covenant of my peace be removed, ſaith the Lord, that hath mercy on thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:37245:22"/>
            <p>Ver. 13. <hi>And all thy children ſhall be taught of the Lord, and great ſhall be the peace of thy children.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is a Prediction of the converſion of the <hi>Jews</hi> in Goſpel-Times. <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.10. <hi>For this is the covenant that I will make with the houſe of Iſrael after thoſe days, ſaith the Lord;</hi> (that is, after the days of their Captivity) <hi>I will put my laws into their mind, and write them in their hearts: and I will be to them a God, and they ſhall be to me a people.</hi> Compare to <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.8, 9, 27, to 34. and <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.22, to 27.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Noah</hi>'s Covenant, or the Diſpenſations of God towards <hi>Noah,</hi> is ſet forth in the Goſpel in a two-fold manner:
<list>
                  <item>1. By way of <hi>Figurative</hi> Alluſion.</item>
                  <item>2. By way of clear Expreſſion.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. By <hi>Figurative</hi> Alluſion, <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.2, 3. <hi>And immediately I was in the ſpirit: and behold, a throne was ſet in heaven, and one ſat on the throne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And he that ſat, was to look upon like a jaſper; and a ſardine ſtone: and there was a rainbow round about the throne, in ſight like unto an emerald.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This was Chriſt, whom God gave to be a Light unto the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and a Covenant of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.8. And the Rain-bow round about the Throne, is an Alluſion unto the Token of <hi>Noah</hi>'s Covenant, which is a Token of Mercy and Grace, and the various providential Diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of God towards his Covenant-People, and the various Gifts and Graces of the Spirit, for the full accompliſhment of all the Promiſes of the Covenant, both to <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile,</hi> eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally about the Latter-day Glory, in calling and converting the <hi>Jews,</hi> with the Fulneſs of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> when God will ſet Chriſt his King upon
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:37245:23"/>his Holy Hill in <hi>Zion,</hi> and make all his Enemies his Foot-ſtool, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.6. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110.1. Which is Typified in that aforeſaid, <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.2, 3.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We have <hi>Noah</hi>'s Covenant recited in the Goſpel, by way of clear Expreſſion, in 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. —<hi>when once the long-ſuffering of God waited in the days of Noah, while the ark was a preparing, wherein few, that is eight ſouls, were ſaved by water. The like figure whereunto, even baptiſm, doth alſo now ſave us,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Here are Six things to be obſerved from theſe Texts aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>1. Here is <hi>Noah</hi>'s Covenant, and the Token thereof, brought down and joined to the Goſpel-Diſpenſation, and the Ordinance of Baptiſm, which is the Initiating Seal of the Covenant in the room of Circumciſion, is alſo joined to it.</p>
            <p>2. As the Waters that drowned the Old World, were Waters of Mercy to <hi>Noah</hi> and his Family, becauſe they bore up the Ark and ſaved them, ſo Chriſt who is a Lyon of Judgment to the Ungodly, is a Lamb of Mercy to his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and is the Ark of God, wherein all the Elect of God are, which is born up by the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God by the Waters of Regeneration unto Salvation, of which Water Baptiſm is a <hi>Figure, Titus</hi> 3.4, 5.</p>
            <p>3. As the Waters that were aſperſed upon the Ark, was a Token of Mercy and Grace to <hi>Noah</hi> and his Seed, ſo is Water-baptiſm to Believers and all their Seed, which is the <hi>Figure</hi> thereof. Now how can this be a like <hi>Figure</hi> to the Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of God towards <hi>Noah,</hi> and all his Seed, if our Children are excluded from Baptiſm, the <hi>Figure</hi> thereof?</p>
            <p>4. This alſo points out unto us the ſubjects of Baptiſm, as well as the Mode thereof. </p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:37245:23"/>
            <p>(1.) The Subjects of Baptiſm: For as <hi>Noah</hi> and all his Children were in the Ark, ſo all Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers and their Seed are in Covenant, and ought to have the <hi>Figure</hi> of <hi>Noah</hi>'s Preſervation, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Baptiſm adminiſtred unto them in their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy: For though all <hi>Noah</hi>'s Seed were not eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally ſaved, yet they were all in Covenant until <hi>Ham</hi> ſinned himſelf out of it, neither do I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that all are ſaved, or ſhall be ſaved, that are baptized, for <hi>Judas,</hi> and <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> and many others, were baptized.</p>
            <p>(2.) It gives good Authority for ſprinkling or pouring Water in Baptiſm; for dipping or plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging is more like a puniſhment of Criminals than the ſolemnizing of Gods Holy Ordinance of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm: It is a nearer Repreſentation or <hi>Figure</hi> of Gods Wrath upon the Old World, than of Grace and Mercy in the Covenant God made with <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> and his Seed, the bleſſing of which is devolved upon us <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and our Children, <hi>Gen.</hi> 12.3. <hi>Acts</hi> 3. <hi>Ye are the children of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and of the covenant which God made with our fathers, ſaying unto Abraham, And in thy ſeed ſhall all the kindreds of the earth be bleſſed. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto you firſt, God having raiſed up his Son Jeſus, ſent him to bleſs you, in turning away every one of you from his iniquities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>5. As the Old ungodly World were all im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merſed and dipped in Wrath and Judgment, ſo proud <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> and all his Hoſt, were plunged and deſtroyed, when he purſued <hi>Iſrael</hi> into the <hi>Red Sea;</hi> but <hi>Iſrael</hi> paſſed through ſafely, and were but ſprinkled, and <hi>ſo were all baptized unto Moſes, in the cloud, and in the ſea,</hi> 1 Cor. 10.1, 2, 3, 4.</p>
            <p>6. And Laſtly, By all theſe things God hath plainly demonſtrated unto us, that his Covenant,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:37245:24"/>Love, and Grace, is the ſame now, as it was ever, both to Believers and their Seed, it is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changable, even like God himſelf that made it.</p>
            <p>3. Mr. <hi>K.</hi> ſaith in <hi>p.</hi> 25. <hi>The Covenant of Works was primarily made with</hi> Adam; <hi>yet another Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition or Miniſtration of it, was given on</hi> Mount Sinai, <hi>and to that Covenant, I did there prove Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion did appertain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But how Mr. <hi>K.</hi> can make theſe things hang together I know not; for Circumciſion was In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted 430 Years before the Ceremonial Law was given upon <hi>Mount Sinai,</hi> and the Moral Law was from <hi>Adam</hi>'s Time; for <hi>Cain</hi> was Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated for breaking the Moral Law: But if the Moral Law was abrogated when the Ceremonial Law was, then hath Mr. <hi>K.</hi> gained a Point; for he ſaith the Subſtance of his other <hi>Arguments</hi> are in this; and to prove it to be a Additional Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration to the Covenant of Works, ſaith he, <hi>The Man that doth thoſe things ſhall live in them:</hi> Which latter is true in it ſelf; for there is no Salvation to be had without Moral Righteouſneſs, though not for it, and ſo he lives in it, in ſincere Obedience, though not in perfect Obedience; for the latter is in Chriſts Obedience; and tho' a Man in doing theſe things lives in them, yet he is not juſtified by his own Obedience to the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Law, but he is juſtified by Chriſts perſonal perfect Obedience, both active and paſſive, to the Law and Juſtice of God; but by the Deeds of the Law no Fleſh can be Juſtified in the ſight of God. Pray mind what the Apoſtle ſaith in <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.17, 21. <hi>And this I ſay, that the covenant that was confirmed before of God in Chriſt, the law which was four hundred and thirty years after, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not diſanul, that it ſhould make the promiſe of none effect.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:37245:24"/>
            <p n="2">2. Here is to be obſerved, that the Everlaſting Covenant God confirmed with <hi>Abraham,</hi> of which Circumciſion was a Token, is called the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, and the <hi>Sinai</hi> Covenant is called the Law; but ſaith the Apoſtle, in <hi>ver.</hi> 21. <hi>Is the law then againſt the promiſes of God? God forbid: for if there had been a law given which could have given life, verily righteouſneſs ſhould have been by the law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ver. 11. <hi>But that no man is juſtiſted the law in the ſight of God, it is evident: for, The juſt ſhall live by faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The Apoſtle doth clearly prove, that the <hi>Sinai</hi> Covenant of Obedience to the Moral Law is ſtill in force, in <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.7, 12. <hi>What ſhall we ſay then? Is the law ſin? God forbid. Nay, I had not known ſin, but by the law: for I had not known luſt, except the law had ſaid, Thou ſhalt not covet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherefore the law is holy; and the commandment holy, and juſt, and good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What think ye now Friend, of all your other Arguments, which you ſay are contained in this one? Are they not ſwallowed up by the Goſpel, even as <hi>Aaron</hi>'s Rod ſwallowed up the Rods of <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Magicians.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Saith Mr. <hi>K.</hi> in <hi>pag.</hi> 24. <hi>The Goſpel Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant ran firſt to all the Elect, that were the natural Off-ſpring of</hi> Abraham, <hi>and then to the Gentiles, and from hence it is ſaid,</hi> Rom. 11. <hi>that when the Jews are called and brought in again, they ſhall be graffed into their own Olive-tree.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. I Anſwer, that if the <hi>Jews</hi> are to be graf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed into their own Olive-tree again, as indeed they muſt, then the Covenant which God made with <hi>Abraham,</hi> and his Seed, is not Repealed, nor Diſſolved.</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:37245:25"/>
            <p n="2">2. That the Elect <hi>Jews</hi> were principally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in the Covenant, I do own; but that none but ſuch were concerned in it, I deny; for had it been ſo, then none had ever been caſt out of Covenant; for God never broke Covenant with his Elect, nor never will: I will produce you, not only his Word, but alſo his Oath for it, in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89. <hi>My covenant will I not break, nor alter the thing that is gone out of my lips.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Once have I ſworn by my holineſs, that I will not lie unto David.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The Covenant which God made with <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> and his Seed, was but one, &amp; is the very ſame now in ſubſtance to the believing <hi>Gentiles,</hi> &amp; their Children, though it is under a new Diſpenſation, and the Middle-wall of partition is broken down, and taken away, and nailed to Chriſts Croſs, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.11, 12, 13, 14. And the <hi>Gentiles</hi> are Fellow-heirs and of the ſame Body, and Partakers of his Promiſe in Chriſt, by the Goſpel; ſo that the Covenant is enlarged, as to the Priviledges there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; for whereas, before the coming in of the Goſpel, it was reſtricted to the <hi>Jews,</hi> and their Seed, now it is to both <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile, Acts</hi> 2.39. Whereas it was clog'd before with Material coſtly Sacrifices, and burdenſome Ceremonies, and ſmarting Ordinances, now it is Meliorated and made eaſier and better, all theſe Shadows are done away, which was the taking away the firſt to eſtabliſh the ſecond, <hi>viz.</hi> to take away the Ceremonial Law to Eſtabliſh the Goſpel.</p>
            <p n="4">4. And laſtly, If none but Elect <hi>Jews</hi> were in the Covenant God made with <hi>Abraham,</hi> and his Seed, at which time the <hi>Gentiles</hi> were reje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and caſt off; for in <hi>Noah</hi>'s Time all the New World were in the Covenant of Grace; How came the <hi>Jews</hi> to ſin themſelves out of it again,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:37245:25"/>when the Elect <hi>Gentiles</hi> and their Seed were ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in? <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.17. For if thoſe <hi>Jews</hi> had been Elected of God they could never have ſinned to ſuch a degree, as to provoke God to caſt them out of Covenant, though they might ſin ſo as to provoke God to puniſh and chaſtiſe them for it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.</p>
            <p n="5">5. And laſtly, Saith Mr. <hi>K.</hi> in <hi>pag.</hi> 27. <hi>And farther to prove the Promiſe of the Covenant of Grace did not belong to</hi> Abrham<hi>'s Natural Seed as ſuch,</hi> Paul <hi>ſhews in</hi> Gal. 3.16. Now to Abraham and to his ſeed was the promiſe made. He ſaith not to ſeeds, as of many, but to thy ſeed, which is Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Friend, though you have charged me falſely with abuſing the Sacred Scriptures, yet give me leave to tell you, you have horribly abuſed this Text, by adding unto it, and diminiſhing from it; for the Words are theſe, in <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Now to Abraham and his ſeed were the promiſes made. He ſaith not, And to ſeeds, as of many; but as of one, And to thy ſeed, which is Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>K.</hi> hath placed <hi>[was the promiſe made,]</hi> which is in the ſingular, inſtead of <hi>[were the promiſes made.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Friend, Was not Chriſt (who is ſtiled this <hi>One</hi> here in this Text) of the Seed of <hi>Abraham?</hi> And was not the Covenant made with him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Foundation of the World, for all the Elect and their Seed? And are not all the Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes <hi>Yea</hi> and <hi>Amen</hi> in Chriſt? Which are the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes in this Text, which you call <hi>the promiſe?</hi> So that this Text intends quite another thing, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hen what you ſeem to infer from it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Let us obſerve what ſtrange Abſurdities to follow.</p>
            <p>1. Would it not be a very abſurd thing, that
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:37245:26"/>God who is a Covenant-keeping God, ſhould keep his Covenant with Believers, and their Seed, from <hi>Adam</hi> to the coming of Chriſt in the Fleſh, which was about 4000 Years, and ſo often renew and eſtabliſh it with Believers and their Seed, by Repeated Promiſes and Sacred Oaths, and that then God ſhould caſt them all off, and Repeal and Diſſolve the Covenant? Pray hear what the Apoſtle ſaith to this, in <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.15. <hi>Brethren, I ſpeak after the manner of men; Though it be but a mans covenant, yet if it be confirmed, no man diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anulleth, or addeth thereto. Viz.</hi> Is a Covenant which is made between Man and Man, ſo ſacred a thing, as that nothing ought to diſanul it, or make it void, and that nothing ought to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded unto it; How much more Sacred is Gods <hi>Everlaſting Covenant,</hi> and not to be diſanulled, made void, nor added unto, by Men?</p>
            <p>2. Is it not an abſurd thing for any Mortals to imagine that the Son of Gods Love, (<hi>John</hi> 3.16.) and the Goſpel of his Grace, ſhould bring more Grace to Adult Believers then the Law, and at the ſame time deſtroy that Grace which their Children enjoyed under the Law? <hi>John</hi> 1.17. <hi>For the law was given by Moſes, but grace and truth came by Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. If this Doctrine were true, then all the Seed of theſe believing <hi>Jews,</hi> which kept Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, were all caſt out, and broken off with the unbelieving <hi>Jews,</hi> and their Seed, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11: 17.</p>
            <p>4. It will follow, that none but Adult belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>Gentiles</hi> were taken into Covenant, and all their Children excluded, which is repugnant to <hi>Acts</hi> 2.39. <hi>For the promiſe is unto you, and to your children, and to all that are afar off, even as many as the Lord our God ſhall call.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:37245:26"/>
            <p>This Promiſe here is the ſame God made with <hi>Adam, Gen.</hi> 3.15. and <hi>Noah, Gen.</hi> 9.9. and <hi>Abraham, Gen.</hi> 17.2, 7. which was made to Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers and their Children.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Theſe Gentlemen that Aſſert the Diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Covenant, wherein are contained Believers and their Seed, never yet undertook to tell us what the perſonal actual Sin was, which theſe poor Babes did commit againſt God, that did provoke him to caſt them all out of Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, who had been in it Four Thouſand Years ſucceſſively; wherefore when you write next about this Subject, be ſo ingenuous as to tell us what the Sin was which theſe young Infants were guilty of, which brought them all under this dreadful condemnation, as to be caſt out of Gods Favour: For unleſs you can do that, all the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments you can raiſe againſt our Principles will only ſerve to prove that you are in a very great <hi>Errour;</hi> for the Covenant God made with <hi>Adam, Noah, Abraham,</hi> and their Seed, is an <hi>Everlaſting Covenant,</hi> ordered in all things, and ſure.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. I will by Gods Aſſiſtance prove that the Infant-Seed of Believers are the proper Subjects of Baptiſm, not to exclude Adult Proſelytes; and in proving this, I ſhall Anſwer all Mr. <hi>B. K</hi>'s. Twenty Seven <hi>Arguments,</hi> as fully and effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually as if I had confuted them one by one; for the Ground of all his <hi>Arguments</hi> is to prove that all Children are excluded the Ordinance of Water-baptiſm in their Infancy: And to effect my Purpoſe I ſhall take this Method, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. I ſhall prove from the Sacred Scriptures, that there is a Command from our Saviour Chriſt for the baptizing young Infants.</item>
               <item>2. There are undeniable Examples for it.</item>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:37245:27"/>
               <item>3. I ſhall prove it from the peculiar Promiſes that are made to the Seed of Believers.</item>
               <item>4. From the Renowned Titles that are given unto them.</item>
               <item>5. From their being under the care, conduct, and Miniſtry of the bleſſed Angels.</item>
               <item>6. And Laſtly, From the tender care and ſweet condeſcending Carriage and Behaviour of our bleſſed Redeemer to the Children of Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, above all other Mens Children in the World.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. There is a poſitive Command for the bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing of Infants, as well as of others, in Chriſts Commiſſion in <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19, 20. <hi>Go and diſciple all nations;</hi> that is, Baptize them; for if you obſerve, Teaching comes after, <hi>Go and diſciple all nations, make them diſciples by baptiſm.</hi> Now, either Children are no part of a Nation, or elſe there were no Children in all theſe Nations, to whom Chriſt ſent his Apoſtles and Miniſters to preach the Goſpel, or elſe Children are every whit as much concerned in the Commiſſion, with a reſpect to Baptiſm, as the Adult: But Children are a great part of a Nation, and for any to imagine, that there were no Children in all theſe Nations is ridiculous; and therefore Children are included in this Commiſſion of our Lords, and ſo they come under the Power and Authority of Chriſts poſitive Command to be baptized.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They Object, Children muſt be taught be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they ought to be baptized, and Children are not capable of being taught, and therefore not capable of baptiſm.</p>
            <p>Pray hear what God ſaith in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59.21. <hi>As for me, this is my covenant with them, ſaith the Lord, My ſpirit that is upon thee, and my words which I
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:37245:27"/>have put in thy mouth, ſhall not depart out of thy mouth, nor out of the mouth of thy ſeed, nor out of the mouth of thy ſeeds ſeed, ſaith the Lord, from henceforth and for ever.</hi> Iſa. 54.13. <hi>And all thy children ſhall be taught of the Lord, and great ſhall be the peace of thy children.</hi> Heb. 8.11. <hi>And they ſhall not teach every man his neighbour, and every man his brother, ſaying, Know the Lord: for all ſhall know me, from the leaſt to the greateſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Teaching of God proceeds from his Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Love, as appears by the aforeſaid Scriptures.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In <hi>Mark</hi> 16.15. there is Chriſts poſitive Command to <hi>preach the Goſpel to every creature,</hi> that is, to ſome of all Ages and Sects, of the Rational Being; therefore Children are concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in this Command, as being a very great part of the Rational Being, and they have a great benefit by the Miniſtry of the Goſpel, which benefit lyeth principally in their Parents being ſo diſciplined and taught, as to be made Believers, at which Inſtant their Children are alſo initiated and planted into the Covenant of Grace, and are holy Children in Gods account, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14. and ſo have a Right to the holy Diſcipline, <hi>viz.</hi> Water-baptiſm, the Initiating Seal of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And Laſtly, There is a Command for Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to hear the Word of the Lord, as well as Adult Perſons, in <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.4. Even as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned all <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Man, Woman, and Child, to appear before God, and renew their Covenant with him, in <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.9, to 13.</p>
            <p>Thus I have proved <hi>A Command</hi> for the bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing all the Infant-Seed of Believers.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I will prove Infant-Baptiſm from clear Examples.</p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:37245:28"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> From the Example of <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt, Mat.</hi> 3. <hi>Then went out to him Jeruſalem and all Judea, and all the regions round about Jordan, And were baptized of him in Jordan, confeſſing their ſins. But when he ſaw many of the Phariſees and Sadducees come to his baptiſm, he ſaid unto them, O generation of vipers, who hath warned you to flee from the wrath to come?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John</hi> baptized all the Natural Seed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> that came to his Baptiſm; he refuſed none, though at the ſame time he exhorted them to Repentance, and not to rely upon their Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant-Relation to <hi>Abraham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ver. 11. <hi>I indeed baptize you with water unto repentance,</hi> &amp;c. So that it doth not appear that <hi>John</hi> baptized none, but them, which were truly penitent.</p>
            <p>1. Here you ſee all the <hi>Jews,</hi> Men, Women, and Children, that came unto <hi>John,</hi> were bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized by him; for all came to his Baptiſm; for Children were a great part of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and of all <hi>Judea, &amp;c.</hi> And therefore Children were not excluded, but were baptized.</p>
            <p>2. The Ordinance of Baptiſm was firſt Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted among the <hi>Jews,</hi> and their Seed, before it was among the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and theirs, many Years; for the <hi>Gentiles</hi> muſt firſt be proſelyted and taken viſibly into Covenant by Diſcipline.</p>
            <p>3. And Laſtly, If <hi>John</hi> had not baptized all Children, how could it be ſaid, that <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and all <hi>Judea,</hi> and all the Region round about <hi>Jordan,</hi> went out to him, and were baptized of him? Therefore it is plain, that all were bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed by him. Now if I ſhould ſay, All my Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhold are baptized, and yet none of my Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are baptized, who are almoſt double in number the reſt of my Family, How could that be true?</p>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:37245:28"/>
            <p>So that it is very plain, from the Example of <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> we have unqueſtionable Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to baptize all our Children in their Infancy.</p>
            <p n="2">2. There are Examples of Infant-baptiſm from the Apoſtles practice; for they baptized whole Houſholds; wherefore if there had been but one Child in all theſe Houſholds that was not bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, it could not properly have been ſaid, that the whole Houſhold were baptized; for children are the principal Upholders of the Houſe; for where there are no children, that Houſe is but of ſhort duration; and it is plain, that believing Parents, and their children, make a holy Houſe, a ſanctified Husband, or a ſanctified Wife, and holy children make one Body, and therefore they ought to be baptized, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.13. <hi>For by one ſpirit are we all baptized, into one body,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Here are whole Houſholds that were bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed by the Apoſtles, <hi>Acts</hi> 18.8. <hi>Acts</hi> 16.14, 15. and <hi>ver.</hi> 30, 31, 33. and ſome others; and alſo whole Houſholds, that were Believers, which we read nothing at all of their Baptiſm.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That Children are a great part of the Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhold is very clear; for by our Saviours Words, Parents and their children onely make the Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhold, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. <hi>For I am come to ſet a man at variance againſt his father, and the daughter againſt her mother,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And a mans foes ſhall be they of his own houſhold.</hi> Theſe were Parents and Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren, not one Servant mentioned: And the Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of <hi>Zarephath,</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 17.15. <hi>And ſhe went, and did according to the ſaying of Elijah: and ſhe, and he, and her houſe did eat many days.</hi> Here was the Woman, and the Prophet, and her Houſe, (that was her Son,) did eat many days; for ſhe had no more in her Family, as in the 12th. <hi>Verſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:37245:29"/>
            <p>Heb. 11. <hi>By faith Noah being warned of God of things not ſeen as yet, moved with fear, prepared an Ark, to the ſaving of his houſe,</hi> &amp;c. That was him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, Wife and Children, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.1, 7.</p>
            <p>So that it is impoſſible Children could be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, if they had any, becauſe the word <hi>Houſhold</hi> includes them; but it would be very ſtrange, if there were no children in all thoſe baptized Families, that are mentioned in the Goſpel only occaſionally; for no doubt but there were many thouſands of Houſholds more, that were baptized in the Apoſtles Time, which they had not the ſame occaſion to mention in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, which we do not read of.</p>
            <p n="4">4. And Laſtly, Though all the Infant-Seed of Believers are Holy Children in Scripture account, yet they are not all ſavingly ſanctified, neither is Water-baptiſm it ſelf ſuch an Ordinance as to convey or infuſe Grace and Holineſs into the Subject baptized, ſo as to unite them to Chriſt by Regeneration; No, that is the Work of the Holy Ghoſt alone in the Baptiſm by Fire.</p>
            <p>Indeed this I do believe, that God may, nay many times doth, while the external Sign of Regeneration and Sanctification is applying with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, work the thing ſignified by his holy Spirit internally within.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee here are clear Examples of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant-Baptiſm, and good Authority for it, unleſs it can be proved that there were no Children in all theſe Nations, that Chriſt commiſſioned his Apoſtles to preach the Goſpel unto.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is clear, that all the Infant-Seed of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers have a Right unto the Ordinance of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, in their Infancy, from the peculiar Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of God made unto them above all other Children in the World.</p>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:37245:29"/>
            <p n="1">1. God hath promiſed to be their God, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 112.2. <hi>His ſeed ſhall be mighty upon the earth: The generation of the upright ſhall be bleſſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pſal. 102.28. <hi>The children of thy ſervants ſhall continue, and their ſeed ſhall be eſtabliſhed before thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29.23. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 44.3. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.22. <hi>Act.</hi> 2.29. Here you ſee are Precious Promiſes made to the Children of Believers, to be fulfilled and accompliſhed in Goſpel-times; and is it rational to conceive, that God would not allow them the Ordinance of Baptiſm, that is now the Seal or Token of the Covenant, wherein all theſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes are contained, which God hath made to the Seed of Believers? Therefore all the Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren of Believers ought to be baptized in their Infancy.</p>
            <p n="4">4. We may infer, that the Infant Seed of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers have a Right to Baptiſm, from the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Titles that are given them: Firſt, they are called Diſciples, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.1, 10. <hi>And certain men which came down from Judea, taught the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and ſaid, Except ye be circumciſed after the manner of Moſes, ye cannot be ſaved.</hi> They did not ſay, After the manner of <hi>Abraham;</hi> No, for they were zealous of the Ceremonial Law. Theſe Men came from <hi>Judea,</hi> where <hi>John</hi> had been baptizing all that came to him: (<hi>ver.</hi> 10.) <hi>Now therefore why tempt ye God, to put a yoke upon the neck of the diſciples, which neither our fathers nor we were able to bear?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it may be Objected, Thoſe were Adult believing <hi>Gentiles,</hi> Which in part is true; but it was to their Children principally; for they which taught them, that they themſelves muſt be circumciſed, did alſo teach them, that their
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:37245:30"/>Children muſt be circumciſed, and that the <hi>Jews</hi> Children muſt be circumciſed likewiſe, as doth clearly appear from <hi>Acts</hi> 21. <hi>Thou ſeeſt, brother, how many thouſands of Jews there are which believe, and they are all zealous of the law. And they are informed of thee, that thou teacheſt all the Jews which are among the Gentiles to forſake Moſes, ſaying, that they ought not to circumciſe their children,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Pray when was this, that the Apoſtle did thus teach the People? Why, do but look back into <hi>Acts</hi> 15. and you will find it was when the Men came down from <hi>Judea,</hi> and preached up Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, and were ſuch Zealots for the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> as that they told the People they could not be ſaved without keeping of it.</p>
            <p>So that it is clear, that theſe Children in <hi>Acts</hi> 11. were of the number of thoſe Diſciples in <hi>Acts,</hi> 15.10. And therefore the Infant-Seed of Believers are Diſciples, and ought to be bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, as being in Chriſts Commiſſion, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19, 20.</p>
            <p>Now a little by way of Query and Expoſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation.</p>
            <p>1. Is it any ways likely that the believing <hi>Jews</hi> would have been brought off from circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſing their Children, without an Ordinance that was equivalent, or better, in the room of it? Eſpecially if we do but conſider, how hard a Task the Apoſtles had to bring them off from it; for they thought they ſhould be damned if they did neglect it, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.1.</p>
            <p>2. If we do but conſider what a great Eſteem the <hi>Jews</hi> hath for the Ordinance of Baptiſm, which may be meaſured by the Queſtion our Saviour put to thoſe Great Men, when they came to him to queſtion his Authority, in <hi>Mark</hi> 11.
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:37245:30"/>29, 30. They did not dare to ſay that <hi>John</hi>'s Baptiſm was of Men, for fear that the People would have ſtoned them.</p>
            <p>3. If it were ſuch a dangerous thing for thoſe Prieſts, Scribes, and Elders, to have denied <hi>John</hi>'s Baptiſm to be of divine Authority, what a dangerous thing would it have been for any Man to have Aſſerted, that all their Children had been caſt out of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Covenant, or to have opened their Mouths againſt Infant-baptiſm, ſeeing the Apoſtles had ſo much adoe to bring them off from Circumciſion, which was the Seal or Token of the Covenant, and did Typifie our Saviours bloody Baptiſm, namely, his Death and Sufferings? </p>
            <p>1. It was a bloody Ordinance, <hi>Exod.</hi> 4.25, 26. So was Chriſts Sufferings, <hi>Luke</hi> 12.50.</p>
            <p>2. It was a painful Ordinance; ſo was Chriſts Sufferings.</p>
            <p>3. It was an Ordinance wherein all the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects were paſſive; ſo was Chriſt in his bloody Baptiſm.</p>
            <p>4. It was an Ordinance of Inciſion, or cutting off the Fleſh; ſo was the Sufferings of Chriſt, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.26. <hi>After threeſcore and two weeks ſhall Meſſiah be cut off, but not for himſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>5. And Laſtly, The Male Children were only to be circumciſed, which did Typifie that Chriſt our Redeemer muſt be a Man, and that of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and the Paſcal Lamb did Type out the ſame: <hi>It muſt be a male of the flock without ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh;</hi> ſo muſt Chriſt be a Male of the Flock, or Tribe of <hi>Judah,</hi> without ſin: But the Females muſt not be circumciſed, becauſe they could not make a True Figure of Chriſt, our <hi>Paſſeover,</hi> which was ſacrificed for us: But the Females have the Ordinance of Child-bearing, which is the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:37245:31"/>True Figure of Regeneration, without which there could have been no Circumciſion.</p>
            <p n="2">2. When Chriſt the Antitype came in the Fleſh, and was offered up a Sacrifice<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for Sin, then both theſe two Ordinances, <hi>viz.</hi> Circumciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and the Paſſeover, were transformed into Baptiſm and the Lords Supper; and whereas the two former did ſhew the Lords Death to come, ſo the two latter do ſhew that the Lord is come, and hath been offered up a Sacrifice for ſin, and Baptiſm is the Sign of Circumciſion, a Seal of the Righteouſneſs of Faith, as ſucceeding Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion.</p>
            <p n="4">4. I challenge Mr. <hi>B. K.</hi> to prove that ever the believing <hi>Jews</hi> children were denied the Ordinance of Baptiſm, or that Infant-baptiſm is any where forbid in the Goſpel.</p>
            <p n="5">5. And Laſtly, Let him alſo prove, if he can, that ever any one Child, either of believing <hi>Jew,</hi> or <hi>Gentile,</hi> did ſtay until he was an Adult Perſon, and then made a confeſſion of his Faith, and was baptized; for no doubt but there were ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thouſands of Believers children, and Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>children, that were Believers, and grown Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, in the Apoſtles Time, whoſe Parents might be baptized by <hi>John</hi> at the firſt Inſtitution of that Ordinance: And would it not be very ſtrange, if they had not been baptized in their Infancy, that we ſhould not read of one that had been baptized when he came to Years of underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? <hi>Timothy's</hi> Mother and Grandmother were both Believers, and he himſelf an Eminent Saint, and he made a great Figure in the Church of Chriſt, and yet we never read of his Baptiſm, but we do of his Circumciſion; but no doubt but as the latter was in his Manhood, ſo the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer was in the time of his Childhood.</p>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:37245:31"/>
            <p>Thus I have proved the Infant-Seed of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers to be Diſciples.</p>
            <p n="2">2. All the Infant-Seed of Believers are called holy Children, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14. Even as the Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were, becauſe they were a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant-People, and yet all <hi>Iſrael</hi> were not ſaved; for with many of them God was not well-plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, neither do I believe that all the Seed of Goſpel-Believers will be ſaved, though they are baptized; but all that are Elected ſhall be ſaved. They are holy by vertue of their being in the Covenant with their Parents; and as Chriſt did not come to deſtroy the Law but to fulfil it, ſo neither did he come to Repeal nor Diſſolve the Covenant, but to confirm it, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9. <hi>And after threeſcore and two weeks ſhall Meſſiah be cut off, but not for himſelf,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And he ſhall confirm the covenant with many for one week,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The Infant-Seed of Believers are under the Miniſtry of the Holy Angels, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.10. <hi>Take heed that ye deſpiſe not one of theſe little ones; for I ſay unto you, that in heaven their angels do al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways behold the face of my Father which is in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi> And look back on the 6th. <hi>verſe,</hi> and you will ſee that they were Children that believed in Chriſt: <hi>Heb.</hi> 1. <hi>Are they not all miniſtring ſpirits, ſent forth to miniſter for them who ſhall be heirs of ſalvation?</hi> The bleſſed Angels have the care and conduct of all the Elect of God, both in their Lives, and at their Deaths, <hi>Luke</hi> 16. <hi>And it came to paſs that the beggar died, and was carryed by the Angels into Abrahams boſome:</hi> That was, into E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Glory; and the Angels are as capable of doing Service for an Elect Infant, both living and dying, as they are for the oldeſt Saint upon Earth, becauſe the Angels are not Acted by any
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:37245:32"/>power of the Creatures; but by the Power of God; therefore the Infant-Seed of Believers have a Right to Baptiſm, in which Ordinance all the Subjects are as paſſive, as all the Subjects of Circumciſion were; and the Children of Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers do make the ſame paſſive Figure in the Church now, as the Children of the <hi>Jews</hi> did in the Church under the Law; for our Saviour tells us, that <hi>of ſuch is the Kingdom of Heaven,</hi> which is the Church.</p>
            <p n="6">6. And Laſtly, To crown all the reſt, Was the ſweet compaſſionate behaviour of our bleſſed Redeemer towards the Infant-Seed of Believers, in <hi>Mark</hi> 10. <hi>And they brought young children unto him, that he ſhould touch them; and his diſciples re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buked thoſe that brought them. But when Jeſus ſaw it, he was much diſpleaſed, and ſaid unto them, Suffer the little children to come unto me, and forbid them not: for of ſuch is the kingdom of God. And he took them up in his arms, put his hands upon them, and bleſſed them.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Here was no bodily Diſtemper complained of, nor no cure wrought upon their Bodies.</item>
               <item>2. Theſe Children were the Infant-Seed of Believers: For if their Parents had not been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled unto Chriſt, they would never have brought their children unto him, to be bleſſed by him.</item>
               <item>3. As they were Adult Believers that brought them to Chriſt, ſo were they alſo which rebuked them that brought them.</item>
               <item>4. And Laſtly, Chriſt did receive them, and laid his Hands on them, and bleſſed them, and alſo prayed.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Thus you ſee, that the ſweet carriage and compaſſionate behaviour of our bleſſed Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, towards theſe little Infants of believing
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:37245:32"/>Parents, doth clearly demonſtaate unto us, that they were in the Covenant, and were baptized before they were thus viſibly brought unto Chriſt, ſeeing that he himſelf laid his hands on them, and bleſſed them; for laying on of Hands in the <hi>Primitive Time</hi> was ſuccedaneous to Baptiſm, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.12, 15, 16, 17.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee it clearly made out, That all the Infant-Seed of Believers have a Right to the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of Baptiſm; and this brings me to take notice of that Query of <hi>B. K</hi>'s. <hi>viz. What Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit is it to a Child to be baptized?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I reply, So might proud carnal Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon have Queried in the Time of Circumciſion, What benefit have our Young Infants by being circumciſed at Eight Days old? But the Apoſtles Anſwer is very compatible to Mr. <hi>K. Rom.</hi> 3.1, 2. <hi>What advantage then hath the Jew? or what profit is there of circumciſion? Much every way: chiefly, becauſe that unto them were committed the Oracles of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Believing <hi>Gentiles</hi> and their Children are one Body, and likewiſe a holy People, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14. And ſo they have a Federal Right unto the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles of God, as <hi>Iſrael</hi> had of old.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Baptiſm is a ſolemn Dedication of our Children unto God, from whom we received them, and it muſt be done by a ſolemn Act, by the Parents conſent in an Ordinance of God, or elſe it is but humane Invention; therefore if it ought not to be done in that Church Ordinance, namely, Baptiſm, then I deſire to know of thoſe Gentlemen that oppoſe it, what Church Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance it muſt be done in, that is more compatible than that of Baptiſm.</p>
            <p n="4">4. And Laſtly, It is the Duty of all Chriſtian Believers to look upon all their Children in their
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:37245:33"/>Infancy, as Elected of God from all Eternity. It is not for us to reprobate any of them in our Minds, and ſay, If I knew which of my Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren were choſen of God, I would dedicate them only unto God in Baptiſm: For that indeed is a ſecret we ought not to pry into; it is Gods Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative only to know which of our Childrens Names are written in his <hi>Book of Election:</hi> But ſeeing they are all called <hi>holy Children,</hi> without exception, our Duty is to hope well of them all, and dedicate them all unto God, in the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Baptiſm, and believe and pray for them all, as if they were all Elected; and we did know it, as long as we do not know any thing to the contrary. But God hath put all the Infant-Seed of Believers in their Infancy, now under the Goſpel, into the Ballance alike, with a reſpect to their Parents knowledge, as if they were Elected in the 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14.</p>
            <p>Thus I have proved ſplendently, That the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant-Seed of Believers are in Covenant, and are the proper Subjects of Baptiſm, not excluding Adult Proſelytes: By which I have fully Anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red all the Arguments that ever were raiſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, and alſo Mr. <hi>B. K</hi>'s. Book, in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, as much as if I had confuted them <hi>Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> by <hi>Argument.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">V. And <hi>Laſtly,</hi> Mr. <hi>B. K.</hi> hath laboured hard to prove, That <hi>the Church State under the Law was only a Carnal Legal Church State, and that it was diſſolved at the Coming of Chriſt in the Fleſh.</hi> And one of his Topping Arguments to prove it to be ſo, is, <hi>That they were a Natural Church, and the Churches under the Goſpel are congregational.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore my buſineſs is to prove the contrary, and I ſhall purſue this Method, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. I ſhall
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:37245:33"/>prove, that the Church is of the ſame Form and Mettle ſubſtantially now, as it was under the Law. 2. That there are the ſame ſort of Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, both for Age and Sects. 3. And Laſtly, The Church lives and feeds upon the ſame ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Food now, as the Church did under the Law.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Church is of the ſame Form and Mettle, I ſhall prove firſt out the <hi>Old Testament,</hi> Zech. 4. <hi>And the angel that talked with me, came again and waked me; as a man that is wakened out of his ſleep, And ſaid unto me, What ſeeſt thou? And I ſaid, I have looked, and behold, a candleſtick all of gold,</hi> &amp;c. Secondly, the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> Rev. 1.20. <hi>The myſtery of the ſeven ſtars which thou ſaweſt in my right hand, and the ſeven golden candleſticks, which thou ſaweſt, are the ſeven churches.</hi> Candleſticks are to ſet up a Light in, and they are of the ſame Mettle, <hi>viz.</hi> Golden Candleſticks. What though there was but one under the Law, and that was National, and now ſeveral and they congregational, yet the Form, Uſe, and Mettle, is the ſame. Suppoſe a Man hath a Tree in his Orchard that hath but one Branch upon it, and that is decaying, and he cuts that off, and graffs ſeveral Branches upon the ſame Stock, that doth not deſtroy the Root, or Stock of the Tree, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.16. <hi>For if the firſt-frruit be holy, the lump is alſo holy: and if the root be holy, ſo are the branches.</hi> The Church-State under the Law was the ſame as it was in <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Time, which was 430 Years before the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and it is the ſame as it was in <hi>Adam</hi>'s Time, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. On this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe the Foundation or Church-State was laid, and as it was in the Beginning, ſo it is now, and ever will be to the Worlds End.</p>
            <p>But ſaith Mr. <hi>K.</hi> in <hi>pag.</hi> 9. <hi>I alſo ask you whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the</hi> Jewiſh <hi>Church, that was ſounded upon the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:37245:34"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:37245:34"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:37245:35"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:37245:35"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:37245:36"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:37245:36"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:37245:37"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:37245:37"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:37245:38"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:37245:38"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:37245:39"/>Old Covenant, is not gone and diſſolved? If ſo, what doth your arguing prove?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I Anſwer, The <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church-State was foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded on the Covenant of Grace, call it what Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant you pleaſe; for <hi>Abraham</hi> had the Goſpel preached unto him when God eſtabliſhed the Covenant with him, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.8. And ſo had <hi>Adam, Gen.</hi> 3.15. And <hi>Noah</hi> was a Goſpel Preacher, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5. And the Church-State is the ſame now as it was before the Diſpenſation of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By the Words of our Saviour himſelf, <hi>Mat.</hi> 21. <hi>Therefore I ſay unto you, The kingdom of God ſhall be taken from you, and given to a nation bringing forth the fruit thereof.</hi> Now if this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God was not the Church-State, in which all the <hi>Jews</hi> then were, pray tell us what King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God this was. 1. It appears that this Kingdom of God was the Church Militant, and not the Church Triumphant. 2. That the Church State was mutable, and yet indiſſolvable. God might remove it from one Nation to another, as he did from the unbelieving <hi>Jews</hi> unto the believing <hi>Gentiles, Mat.</hi> 21.43. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.17. But the State of the Church is the ſame, and is unalterable. 3. There were the ſeven Churches of <hi>Aſia</hi> diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; but that did not deſtroy the Church State no more than the Excommunicating Members out of a particular Church doth.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Apoſtle makes it appear plainly, that the Church State is the ſame now, as ever it was, before the Incarnation of Chriſt, in <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. <hi>Now therefore ye are no more ſtrangers and forreigners, but fellow-citizens with the ſaints, and of the hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhold of God; And are built upon the foundation of the apoſtles and prophets, Jeſus Chriſt himſelf being the chief corner ſtone; In whom all the building fitly
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:37245:39"/>framed together, groweth unto an holy temple in the Lord: In whom you alſo are builded together for an habitation of God through the Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now pray Mr. <hi>K.</hi> what do you think? Was the State of the <hi>Jews</hi> Church a carnal legal Church State? Whereas you hear it was a Habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation for God through the Spirit, and Jeſus Chriſt the chief corner Stone. Did God dwell in a carnal Church? Or was Chriſt ever the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of a carnal Church? Which muſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily follow as the conſequence of this carnal Poſition.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In <hi>pag.</hi> 43. ſaith Mr. <hi>K. I ask whether or no Chriſt did not remove by the Goſpel Diſpenſation, all the Wheat out of the old Barn, nay, and pull down that Barn?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Chriſt did not pull down that Barn, but he purged the Floor of it, neither did he remove the Wheat out of it, but he did winnow and fan away all the chaffy Hypocrites, the unbelie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>Jews,</hi> and gathered his Elect <hi>Gentile</hi>-wheat into his Garner, Kingdom, or Church, and <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt</hi>'s Teſtimony is ſufficient to prove this; let any Man deny this if they dare, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3. <hi>I indeed baptize you with water unto repentance; but he that cometh after me, is mightier then I, whoſe ſhoes I am not worthy to bear: he ſhall baptize you with the holy Ghoſt, and with fire. Whoſe ſan is in his hand, and he will throughly purge his floor, and gather his wheat into the garner: but he will burn up the chaff with unquenchable fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here are Two Things to be obſerved from this Text; The <hi>Firiſt</hi> is, A threatning the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſion of the unbelieving <hi>Jews;</hi> and the <hi>Second,</hi> A Prediction of the calling and converſion of the Elect <hi>Gentiles,</hi> which was the taking the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God from the <hi>Jews,</hi> and giving it to the <hi>Gentiles.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:37245:40"/>
            <p n="2">2. The Church is the ſame now in a ſenſe, as it was under the Law, with a reſpect to the Members of it; for as the <hi>Jews</hi> and their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, were the Members of it under the Law, ſo Believers and their children, are the Members of it under the Goſpel, <hi>Mat.</hi> 19. <hi>But Jeſus ſaid, Suffer the little children, and forbid them not to come unto me: for of ſuch is the kingdom of heaven.</hi> Eph. 3.6. <hi>That the Gentiles ſhould be fellow-heirs, and of the ſame body, and partakers of his promiſe in Chriſt, by the goſpel.</hi> Which Promiſe you have in <hi>Acts</hi> 2.39. which is to Believers and their children.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And Laſtly, The Church under the Law did live and feed upon the ſame Spiritual Food as the Church now doth, and was a baptized Church, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. <hi>And were all baptized unto Moſes in the cloud, and in the ſea; And did all eat the ſame ſpiritual meat;</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>K.</hi> pray tell me how was it poſſible that a carnal legal Church could live upon Spiritual Food? Sir, you ſhould think before you write: I am ſorry you can diſtinguiſh no better of thoſe Profound Myſteries of the Goſpel. Thus you ſee your carnal Conception of the Church State utterly confuted, and the Church proved to be the ſame now, as it was from the Beginning, and ever will be while there is a Saint upon Earth; and if you do write again, bring better Arguments to Town with you, or elſe you had as good ſay nothing, And ſo <hi>Farewell.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="postscript">
               <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
               <p>MR. <hi>B. K.</hi> in <hi>pag.</hi> 35. hath made a Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of my Words in Anſwer to Mr. <hi>H. C</hi>'s. late Book, which he calls unſeemly, ſcoffing,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:37245:40"/>opprobrious Language; therefore I have made a Collection of Mr. <hi>H. C</hi>'s. Language to me, and let any Man judge whether I have not been mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate; for <hi>Evil Communication corrupts Good Manners.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In <hi>pag.</hi> 1. ſaith Mr. <hi>H. C. What is this Man reſolved to ſet himſelf in a poſture of war againſt God and his Word? An Advocate againſt the Truth, blinded with prejudice. Theſe are in the room of an Oculiſt, to open his eyes to behold his Errour in Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> Pag. 2. <hi>He makes a Man of Straw, and fights with it, or his own Shadow.</hi> If it be not from Ignorance, then it is from a worſe Root; he deſerves <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s Title, The hard Father of Infants. Page 3. <hi>What would this Man make a new Bible? Had he the Notion by Inſpiration?</hi> I do not wonder the Man is ſo well pleaſed with an unſcriptural Baptiſm, when he Aſſerts an unſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural way of ſaving Infants. He is almoſt at his wits-end, and famiſhed for want of Arguments, and ſo will catch at any thing. Page 4. <hi>You are in the Pound, Sir, get out if you can.</hi> His Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are ſo feeble, that it is a tottering Fence. Would any Man but one void of common ſenſe, urge ſuch Scriptures for Infants Inherent Faith. Page 6. <hi>When will you ceaſe to pervert the right Word of the Lord.</hi> Page 7. <hi>Get out of this Priſon as well as you can.</hi> Page 8. <hi>Pray Sir, go to School again, and learn better Logick.</hi> Page 10. <hi>Did ever Man ſpeak more impertinently: Theſe Lines of his muſt be written through ignorance, inadvertency, or worſe.</hi> Pag. 11. <hi>Who labours all he can to blacken the Ways of God, and render the Profeſſors of it as odious as poſſible: Doth he not acquire the Name of an exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite Calumniator? Is not this the Man</hi> David <hi>ſpeaks of, that travelleth with iniquity, conceived miſchief, and brought forth falſehood? Remember, remember</hi>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:37245:41"/>John Child, <hi>whoſe chief cauſe of deſperation was his ſpeaking and writing againſt thoſe very people of God you now do.</hi> Page 14. <hi>Here you have brought your ſelf again into a Nooſe, and I cannot help it.</hi> In his former Book before ever I writ againſt their Opinion, he ſaid, Infants Baptiſm of Earth and Humane Invention, and Rantizing and a Relique of Antichriſt. So much for Mr. <hi>B. K</hi>'s. Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Brother Mr. <hi>H. C.</hi> whom he hath ſo highly vindicated in his Book; but in point of Juſtice and common honeſty, he ought to have laid down this opprobrious Language of Mr. <hi>H. C.</hi> againſt me.</p>
               <p>Now in the ſecond place I ſhall compare what Mr. <hi>B. K.</hi> charges me with, in the 5 <hi>Chap.</hi> of his Book, againſt Mr. <hi>H. C.</hi> and let us ſee which maketh the blackeſt Figure.</p>
               <p>Saith Mr. <hi>K. I ſhall begin with Mr.</hi> Shutes <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becoming, ſcoffing Expreſſions, as they lie here and there in his Book.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In</hi> page 4. <hi>he ſaith, He will not render Railing for Railing, yet in</hi> page 5. <hi>you will find theſe Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, ſpeaking to Mr.</hi> C. You have charged me falſely; you boggled and juggled with the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; <hi>yet he has not made either of theſe things ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear. In</hi> page 5. <hi>he ſaith,</hi> Here thou haſt the Cavils of the Adverſary anſwered.</p>
               <p>This Man matters not what he ſaith to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote his Opinion; juſt like the <hi>Papiſts</hi> who hold that <hi>The End ſanctifieth the Means;</hi> for if you look into my Book, in <hi>page</hi> aforeſaid, you will find it to be only a Repetition of what is ſaid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me in the <hi>Preface</hi> of Mr. <hi>H. C</hi>'s. Book; and let any Man read where I have charged Mr. <hi>H. C.</hi> with perverting the Scriptures, and look into his Book and ſee if it be not true.</p>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:37245:41"/>
               <p>Again, Saith Mr. <hi>K.</hi> of me, <hi>Mr. C. doth as little Boys, that make a thing of Rags, in imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Cock, and when they have ſet it up,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>This was only to Illuſtrate an abominable Falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood Mr. <hi>C.</hi> hath fixed upon me, and then rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed an Argument from it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In</hi> page 46. <hi>he ſaith,</hi> Mr. <hi>C.</hi> is troubled with the Grumbling in his Gizzard. But this is falſe, I did not ſay <hi>his</hi> Gizzard, but <hi>the</hi> Gizzard: But you are very ſubject to miſtakes; but I find it is always in favour of your own Opinion, which looks as if it were wilful.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He ſaith in</hi> page 57. <hi>that</hi> Mr. <hi>C.</hi> is pleaſed to mock at Habitual Faith.</p>
               <p>This is true, and I wonder how you dare deny it.</p>
               <p>Saith Mr. <hi>K. He renders me worſe than the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil,</hi> pag. 116. The Devil left out part of a Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture once, to tempt our Saviour with, but in my weak Judgment (<hi>ſaith Mr.</hi> Shute) this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour hath done it three times, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In</hi> page 82. <hi>he ſaith,</hi> (<hi>ſpeaking of Mr.</hi> C.) Was there ever ſuch Legerdemain played with the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Scriptures?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In</hi> page 23. <hi>he cries out,</hi> O for ſhame ceaſe from bringing your carnal Reaſon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In</hi> page 24. Where are you now with your humane, invented, lame, decrepit Salvation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In</hi> page 56. <hi>he abuſes Mr.</hi> Danvers <hi>who is dead.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here is all the ſcoffing Expreſſions, or oppro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brious Language, as Mr. <hi>K.</hi> calls it, as he pick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed together, as they lie up and down in my <hi>Book.</hi> Now let any Man of ſenſe, or common honeſty, but conſider the Provocations that Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> gave me, and then judge whether I have not been moderate: but Mr. <hi>K.</hi> (the wiſe Man)
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:37245:42"/>telleth us, that <hi>to acquit the Guilty, and condemn the Innocent, are alike Abomination.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as for this <hi>Book</hi> of Mr. <hi>Benjamin Keaches,</hi> I will only ſay this of it, to wit, Had I writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten it, People would have been prone to ſay, that there was much of the Malice of Satan in it, and but little of the Subtilty of the Serpent, and nothing of the Innocency of the Dove to be found therein, and that there was neither Parts, nor Good Manners, but a complication of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Zeal, Embeliſhed with Errours, and falſe Doctrines and Poſitions.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <p>London, <hi>Printed for the Authour, and Sold by</hi> Nathaniel Hiller: <hi>Where you may alſo have his other Books,</hi> Viz. An Antidote to prevent the Prevalency of <hi>Anabaptiſm,</hi> 4to. <hi>Price ſtitcht</hi> 6 d. The Vindication of the <hi>Antidote,</hi> 12mo. bound One Shilling. An Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Hercules Collins</hi> Laſt Shift, 12mo. <hi>Price ſtitcht in Blew Paper,</hi> One Penny.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
